<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Timothy's lesson: or, a summary relation of the historical part of Holy scripture plainly and familiarly comprized in metre, for the help of memory, and instruction of the ignorant. By E.G. Master in Arts, and physician of the hospital of St. Bartholomew, of the foundation of Queen Elizabeth, of the city of Gloucester.</title>
            <title>Little Timothie, his lesson, a summarie relation of the historicall part of Holy Scripture</title>
            <author>Graile, Edmond, b. ca. 1577.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85508</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1467A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223566</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899610</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899610</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154167</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85508)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154167)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2402:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Timothy's lesson: or, a summary relation of the historical part of Holy scripture plainly and familiarly comprized in metre, for the help of memory, and instruction of the ignorant. By E.G. Master in Arts, and physician of the hospital of St. Bartholomew, of the foundation of Queen Elizabeth, of the city of Gloucester.</title>
                  <title>Little Timothie, his lesson, a summarie relation of the historicall part of Holy Scripture</title>
                  <author>Graile, Edmond, b. ca. 1577.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The fourth impression corrected and amended.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>72, 71-82 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year, 1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First published in 1611 as "Little Timothie, his lesson, a summarie relation of the historicall part of Holy Scripture".</note>
                  <note>E.G. = Edmond Graile.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  History of Biblical events --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154167:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154167:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154167:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154167:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="blackletterType">Timothy</hi>'s <hi rend="blackletterType">Leſſon:</hi> Or, A SUMMARY RELATION Of the Hiſtorical Part of HOLY SCRIPTURE, Plainly and familiarly Comprized in Metre, for the Help of Memory, and Inſtruction of the Ignorant.</p>
            <p>By <hi>E. G.</hi> Maſter in Arts, and Phyſician of the Hoſpital of St. <hi>Bartholomew,</hi> of the Foundation of Queen ELIZABETH, of the City of <hi>GLO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CESTER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Fourth Impreſſion Corrected and Amended.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>DEUT. 11.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>You ſhall teach them your Children, ſpeaking of them, when thou ſittest in thine Houſe, and when thou walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est by the way, when thou liest down, and when thou riſest up.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>COLOS. 3.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Let the Word of Christ dwell plenteouſly in you; teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and admoniſhing your ſelves in Pſalms, and Hymns, and ſpiritual Songs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:154167:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:154167:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>In</hi> MOMUM.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WAS <hi>Momus</hi> (trow you) whelp'd in Butcher's Stall,</l>
               <l>That he reſembles ſo that greedy kind?</l>
               <l>For mark: the worſt that is of men let fall,</l>
               <l>Lying in midſt of better Fare, half pin'd,</l>
               <l>He chambers, as a bait pleaſing his mind.</l>
               <l>Fie on him, fie, that he ſo curriſh lie,</l>
               <l>Should joy in that, which others do defie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Or was he of that Cur's moſt ſpiteful Brood,</l>
               <l>Which ſate in Crib, keeping the Ox from meat?</l>
               <l>For he from others keeps that wholſom Food,</l>
               <l>Which (hungry Souls) they ſeek for with their ſweat,</l>
               <l>And yet himſelf diſdains thereof to eat.</l>
               <l>O curſed Envy! that to ſtray the more,</l>
               <l>Will even himſelf lead way unto death's door.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Or rather ſprang he from that helliſh Hound,</l>
               <l>That welcome damned Souls to <hi>Pluto</hi>'s place?</l>
               <l>He ſo doth triumph when ought may be found</l>
               <l>In others, that may turn to their diſgrace.</l>
               <l>(O worthy progeny! O noble race!)</l>
               <l>What e're he deemed was, be ſure of this,</l>
               <l>Were he a <hi>God,</hi> yet now a <hi>Dog</hi> he is.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What, what a <hi>Dog?</hi> and ſhould his ſnarling bay,</l>
               <l>Scare men from that the wiſe have healthful tri'd?</l>
               <l>No, worthy <hi>Jaſon</hi> held on in his way,</l>
               <l>Tho' he might ſeem by Sea and Land deny'd,</l>
               <l>By Bulls repell'd, by Dragons fell envied.</l>
               <l>Shall hope of Treaſures earthly ſo inflame,</l>
               <l>And ſhall not heavenly much more do the ſame?</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:154167:4"/>
            <head>The Author to the Curious READER.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> Leave Perfection of a Poet's Skill,</l>
               <l>(which doth with ſilver Rays poor Ruſticks daunt</l>
               <l>To <hi>Silveſter's,</hi> and to <hi>Du Barta's</hi> quill,</l>
               <l>and ſuch as harbour where the <hi>Muſes</hi> haunt;</l>
               <l>Bathing in Cryſtal Streams of rare Conceits,</l>
               <l>conceiting what they liſt of any ſubject,</l>
               <l>Subjecting whatſoever them delights,</l>
               <l>unto their Wit and Art, their natures object.</l>
               <l>To ſuch leave I, the Majeſty</l>
               <l>of Poetry divine:</l>
               <l>More rife is their Dexterity,</l>
               <l>their Wits more ripe than mine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There needs no Garland where the Wine is good,</l>
               <l>nor Colours, where the Subſtance is moſt pure:</l>
               <l>Sincerity by Truth hath ever ſtood,</l>
               <l>and ſhall, ſo long as doth the Truth endure,</l>
               <l>More Truth than Sacred Verity,</l>
               <l>no Creature can require.</l>
               <l>And who ſo likes Simplicity,</l>
               <l>lo here his full Deſire.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="lesson">
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:154167:4"/>
               <head>THE FIRST PART Of the SUM of the HOLY HISTORY.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>I.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>IN the Beginning GOD alone,</l>
                  <l>did Heaven and Earth create;</l>
                  <l>He ſpake the Word, and it was done,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Geneſis.</hi> Chap. 1.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>as Scriptures do relate.</l>
                  <l>The Earth had neither Form nor Face,</l>
                  <l>the Darkneſs covered all,</l>
                  <l>When thus he made in ſix days ſpace,</l>
                  <l>the Creatures great and ſmall.</l>
                  <l>The firſt Day he commanded Light,</l>
                  <l>The Darkneſs to prevent:</l>
                  <l>The ſecond Day he rear'd in ſight,</l>
                  <l>the ſtately Firmament:</l>
                  <l>The third, the Earth with Fruits adorn'd,</l>
                  <l>the ſwelling Sea debars;</l>
                  <l>The fourth, the Sun and Moon were form'd,</l>
                  <l>with all the Glorious Stars:</l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:154167:5"/>
                  <l>The fifth, the Fiſh with Scales and Fins,</l>
                  <l>and then the feathered Foul:</l>
                  <l>The ſixth, the Beaſts and creeping things,</l>
                  <l>and then that living Soul,</l>
                  <l>Which that one God, in Perſons Three,</l>
                  <l>did make by Conſultation,</l>
                  <l>With purpoſe that the ſame ſhould be,</l>
                  <l>the Mirror of Creation.</l>
                  <l>Even Male, and Female perfect man,</l>
                  <l>right Holy, Wiſe, and Juſt:</l>
                  <l>For he did bear God's Image then,</l>
                  <l>though he were made of Duſt.</l>
                  <l>Thus having finiſh't all with ſpeed,</l>
                  <l>and bleſt them, and proteſted,</l>
                  <l>That each thing made was good indeed,</l>
                  <l>the ſeventh Day he reſted.</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Adam</hi>'s Aid, who was alone,</l>
                  <l>the Lord God formed <hi>Eve:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Fleſh of his fleſh, Bone of his bone,</l>
                  <l>and unto them did give,</l>
                  <l>A Sovereign Power in <hi>Paradiſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>to rule by Sea and Land.</l>
                  <l>And all the Creatures did rejoyce,</l>
                  <l>to do what they command;</l>
                  <l>And all the Fruits were theirs for meat,</l>
                  <l>that in the Garden grew;</l>
                  <l>Save one alone, which if they eat,</l>
                  <l>Death certain ſhall enſue.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Eve</hi> for all that liſtened</l>
                  <l>unto the Serpent's lies,</l>
                  <l>And took and eat the Fruit forbid;</l>
                  <l>yea, <hi>Adam</hi> ate likewiſe,</l>
                  <l>And thereby thought like God to be;</l>
                  <l>but for this great Offence,</l>
                  <l>Poor Souls! to ſhame and miſery</l>
                  <l>they were caſt out from thence.</l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:154167:5"/>
                  <l>Now wretched Man was wrapt in woe,</l>
                  <l>and in his loyns his Heirs,</l>
                  <l>For curſed and corrupt they go:<note place="margin">Verſe <hi>15.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>yet to prevent deſpairs,</l>
                  <l>God promiſed them to reſtore</l>
                  <l>unto a State more ſtable,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Eve</hi> unto her Husband bore,<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cain</hi> and his brother <hi>Abel.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Abel</hi> was ſlain by curſed <hi>Cain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>who did his Goodneſs ſcorn,<note place="margin">Anno mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di, 130.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>But <hi>Evah</hi> did conceive again,</l>
                  <l>and godly <hi>Seth</hi> was born.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>II.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>FRom <hi>Seth</hi> did ſpring a Race of Men</l>
                  <l>religious and upright,</l>
                  <l>Yea <hi>Henoch</hi> walkt with God, and then</l>
                  <l>was taken out of ſight.</l>
                  <l>His Grand-child <hi>Lamech</hi> did beget</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Noah:</hi> and then began,<note place="margin">Anno 1056</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Sons of God their face to ſet,</l>
                  <l>on Daughters fair of Man:</l>
                  <l>Thence Giants came and mungrel kind,<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>on whom the Lord did frown,</l>
                  <l>And for their ſin and wicked mind,</l>
                  <l>did threat the World to drown.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Noah</hi> alone on Earth did live,</l>
                  <l>uprightly; him God ſent,</l>
                  <l>And did an hundred Years them give,</l>
                  <l>and twenty to repent.</l>
                  <l>Mean while built <hi>Noah</hi> at his Charge,</l>
                  <l>an Ark three ſtories high:</l>
                  <l>The wicked World liv'd ſtill at large,</l>
                  <l>and dream'd that <hi>Noe</hi> did lie:</l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:154167:6"/>
                  <l>Till Fountains burſt, and open ſtood,</l>
                  <l>Heaven's windows all,<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note> for rain,</l>
                  <l>Which quickly caus'd a fearful Flood,</l>
                  <l>for down it pours amain,</l>
                  <l>And all the Earth with ruin fills;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 1656.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Men, Beaſts, and Birds muſt die,</l>
                  <l>When as the Flood above the Hills</l>
                  <l>flow'd fifteen Cubits high.</l>
                  <l>Which rag'd well near a Year about,</l>
                  <l>and then was <hi>Noah</hi> bidden</l>
                  <l>To bring thoſe living Creatures out,</l>
                  <l>which in the Ark were hidden.</l>
                  <l>And out they came, both they and theirs,</l>
                  <l>four Women and four Men,</l>
                  <l>The unclean Creatures all by pairs,</l>
                  <l>the clean by ſevens; and then,</l>
                  <l>They offer'd Sacrifice,<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>8.</hi>
                     </note> God ſmell'd</l>
                  <l>a ſmell of Reſt; wherefore</l>
                  <l>He promiſed though Man rebell'd</l>
                  <l>to drown the World no more:</l>
                  <l>And plac'd the Rainbow for a pledge</l>
                  <l>and did again vouchſafe</l>
                  <l>To Man, a Sovereign Priviledge</l>
                  <l>above the Beaſts,<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>9.</hi>
                     </note> and gave</l>
                  <l>Their fleſh for Food. Thus having made</l>
                  <l>a Covenant of Peace,</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Noah</hi> and his Sons; he bad</l>
                  <l>they ſhould Mankind increaſe.</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Japhet</hi> did the Gentiles ſpring,</l>
                  <l>of <hi>Cham</hi> the <hi>Canaanite,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who curſt was for uncovering</l>
                  <l>his Father's ſhameful ſight,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Sem</hi> unto the Bleſſed Line,</l>
                  <l>was Heir, and from him came,</l>
                  <l>A Race and Progeny Divine</l>
                  <l>to Father <hi>Abraham.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:154167:6"/>
                  <l>Now all the World, in ſpeech was one,</l>
                  <l>and did to build conſpire</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Babel,</hi> and confuſion</l>
                  <l>they gained for their hire.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>III.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>THis <hi>Abraham</hi> a faithful Man,</l>
                  <l>left Land and Kindred all,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 2008.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And wandring up and down he ran</l>
                  <l>where e're his God did call.</l>
                  <l>From <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r</hi> he went to <hi>Canaan,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. <hi>12.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>with <hi>Sara</hi> and with <hi>Lot,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To ſettle there he ſcarce began</l>
                  <l>but that by Famine hot,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Aegypt</hi> he was forc'd to flie,</l>
                  <l>where fearing much his life,</l>
                  <l>Before King <hi>Pharaoh</hi> fainingly</l>
                  <l>he did deny his Wife.</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Bethel</hi> he goes back again,<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>13.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>where Strife began to grow,</l>
                  <l>'Twixt <hi>Lot</hi> and him; for Wealth amain,</l>
                  <l>did in upon them flow.</l>
                  <l>Old <hi>Abraham,</hi> with humble Heart,</l>
                  <l>to younger <hi>Lot</hi> gave place,</l>
                  <l>And in diſtreſs did take his part</l>
                  <l>and reſcue him in chaſe.<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>14.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Melchizedec</hi> did him meet and bleſs,</l>
                  <l>but childleſs ſtill he ſtaid,</l>
                  <l>Till <hi>Iſhmael;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. <hi>16.</hi>
                     </note> and that increaſe</l>
                  <l>was but by <hi>Sara</hi>'s Maid:</l>
                  <l>Yet God by ſpecial Promiſes,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.16.15.5.17.6. <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>himſelf did often tie,</l>
                  <l>As Heavens Stars, and ſand of Seas,</l>
                  <l>his Seed to multiply.</l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:154167:7"/>
                  <l>And ſeal'd it with a Sacrament,</l>
                  <l>to him and his Heirs Male;</l>
                  <l>When ſolemnly he did appoint,</l>
                  <l>to circumciſe them all.</l>
                  <l>Mean time he did him entertain,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.23.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>very familiarly;</l>
                  <l>Much like a Friend,<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>18.</hi>
                     </note> as was moſt plain,</l>
                  <l>when <hi>Sodom</hi>'s ſinful cry</l>
                  <l>Did pierce the Skies, and God down came,</l>
                  <l>and if but Ten good Men</l>
                  <l>Could there been found; for <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>the Lord had ſpar'd it then.</l>
                  <l>So Fire and Brimſtone fearfully</l>
                  <l>from Heaven fell apace,</l>
                  <l>And furnace-like the ſmoak did fly:<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>19.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>juſt <hi>Lot</hi> in better caſe,</l>
                  <l>To little <hi>Zoar</hi> fled for life,</l>
                  <l>where in a drunken mood,</l>
                  <l>On's Daughters (having loſt his Wife)</l>
                  <l>he got a * curſed Brood.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>IV.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>THence <hi>Abraham</hi> went to <hi>Gerar</hi> Land,<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>20.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>where he again for fear,</l>
                  <l>Deny'd his Wife, but by God's Hand,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Abimelech</hi> did forbear.</l>
                  <l>Long had he waited, hope was paſt,</l>
                  <l>yet ſtill he did believe;</l>
                  <l>And God remembred him at laſt,</l>
                  <l>and <hi>Sara</hi> did Conceive:<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>21.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And in her old Age <hi>Iſaac</hi> bare,</l>
                  <l>and nurſt him on her knee,</l>
                  <l>And joyful <hi>Abram</hi> did not ſpare</l>
                  <l>to make a feaſt; but ſee</l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:154167:7"/>
                  <l>This only Son, and only Heir,</l>
                  <l>of Promiſe God Commands,</l>
                  <l>To be both ſlain,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 2108</note> and burnt with fire</l>
                  <l>and that by <hi>Abram</hi>'s hand.</l>
                  <l>Well: he obey'd, and call'd his Men,</l>
                  <l>Wood, Knife, and ſome he took,</l>
                  <l>On, to the place they go, and when</l>
                  <l>was bent the deadly Stroke</l>
                  <l>God ſtaid his hand, and in the ſtead</l>
                  <l>of <hi>Iſaac</hi> there was ty'd,</l>
                  <l>A Ram for Sacrifice. Indeed</l>
                  <l>here <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Faith was try'd.<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>22.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>His Son thus ſpar'd, his godly Care</l>
                  <l>was next about to ſpy,</l>
                  <l>For him a Wife, and therefore ſware</l>
                  <l>his Man's Fidelity.<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>24.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who full religiouſly perform'd</l>
                  <l>the Office on him laid,</l>
                  <l>And with <hi>Rebeckah</hi> ſoon return'd,</l>
                  <l>a fair and vertuous Maid;</l>
                  <l>Whom <hi>Iſaac</hi> married, but ſtill,</l>
                  <l>She barren was, they pray'd:</l>
                  <l>God heard, and granted all their Will,<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>25.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and further to her ſaid;</l>
                  <l>The Babes that in her Womb did ſtrive,</l>
                  <l>were Twins and Nations twain,</l>
                  <l>The younger ſhould prevail and thrive,</l>
                  <l>the elder ſhould remain</l>
                  <l>A ſervant: <hi>Eſau</hi> was his Name,</l>
                  <l>and as he Veniſon ſought,</l>
                  <l>And back again well wearied came,</l>
                  <l>his Brother <hi>Jacob</hi> bought</l>
                  <l>His Birth-right for a Meſs of Broth,</l>
                  <l>mean while was <hi>Iſaac</hi> bleſſed,</l>
                  <l>Though envious Philiſtines be wroth,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 26. <hi>ver.</hi> 14, 15.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and him with Wrongs oppreſſed.</l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:154167:8"/>
                  <l>When Age came on and Eyes waxt dim,</l>
                  <l>then ſolemnly he meant,</l>
                  <l>To bleſs his Son, requiring him,</l>
                  <l>Veniſon for that intent.</l>
                  <l>About goes <hi>Eſau</hi> with his Bow,</l>
                  <l>but <hi>Jacob</hi> doth prevent him;</l>
                  <l>The means his Mother did him ſhow,</l>
                  <l>and cunningly preſent him,<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>In <hi>Eſau</hi>'s Clothes and Skins of Kids,</l>
                  <l>unto his Father; who</l>
                  <l>Miſtruſts the Voice and therefore bids,</l>
                  <l>come near to feel and know.</l>
                  <l>With fat of Earth, and Heaven's Dew,</l>
                  <l>with happy Seed and Kin,</l>
                  <l>He bleſt him (reverend was the ſhew)</l>
                  <l>and then came <hi>Eſau</hi> in.</l>
                  <l>And he with Tears and piteous Moan,</l>
                  <l>the Bleſſing ſought in vain,</l>
                  <l>He came too late, alas 'twas gone,</l>
                  <l>with that he beat his Brain</l>
                  <l>To ſeek and work Revenge, and then</l>
                  <l>the days (quoth he) make ſpeed,</l>
                  <l>Of mourning for my Father, when</l>
                  <l>I'll ſlay him for this Deed.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>V.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>THen did <hi>Rebeckah</hi> forthwith call,</l>
                  <l>and ſend <hi>Jacob</hi> away,</l>
                  <l>Leſt <hi>Eſau</hi> ſhould upon him fall,</l>
                  <l>his bloody Vow to pay.</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Iſaac</hi> charg'd him (taking leave)</l>
                  <l>to play a wiſer part,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Eſau,</hi> who did vex and grieve,</l>
                  <l>by heathen Wives his Heart.<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>21.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:154167:8"/>
                  <l>But he ſhould to his Uncle go,</l>
                  <l>and match in godly Race,</l>
                  <l>And bleſſing ſhould be with him; ſo,</l>
                  <l>he went out from their face:</l>
                  <l>As he in fields that night did ſleep,</l>
                  <l>in <hi>Haran</hi> on a Stone;</l>
                  <l>By Dream he ſaw a Ladder ſteep</l>
                  <l>from Heaven; and thereon</l>
                  <l>The Angels paſſing, and above</l>
                  <l>God ſtanding all in view,</l>
                  <l>The bleſſed Promiſe of his Love,</l>
                  <l>with <hi>Jacob</hi> to renew.</l>
                  <l>There <hi>Jacob</hi> vow'd the Lord to fear:</l>
                  <l>thence on he went apace,</l>
                  <l>Inquiring in the fields to hear,</l>
                  <l>of <hi>Laban</hi>'s dwelling place.</l>
                  <l>The Shepherds ſhew'd him readily,<note place="margin">Chap. 29.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>his Couſin <hi>Rachel</hi> there:</l>
                  <l>Whom he ſaluted chearfully,</l>
                  <l>and ſhe could not forbear,</l>
                  <l>But ran and carry'd home the News:</l>
                  <l>then <hi>Laban</hi> hies to meet him,</l>
                  <l>To dwell there he muſt not refuſe,</l>
                  <l>where all his Kindred greet him:</l>
                  <l>A match was made, and ſeven Years</l>
                  <l>for <hi>Rachel</hi> ſerve he muſt;</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Leah</hi> in the light appears,</l>
                  <l>ſo falſe was <hi>Laban</hi>'s truſt.</l>
                  <l>Well, ſeven more he was content,</l>
                  <l>to ſerve for his Beloved,</l>
                  <l>And thought the time full quickly ſpent,<note place="margin">Chap. 29. <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. Chap. 31.38, 39.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>though full of Toyl it proved.</l>
                  <l>God bleſſed <hi>Laban</hi> for his ſake,</l>
                  <l>but him he bleſt much more.</l>
                  <l>Whatever Wages he did take,</l>
                  <l>to him was Gain and Store.</l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:154167:9"/>
                  <l>Then <hi>Laban</hi> did envy his Wealth,</l>
                  <l>yet loath to let him go,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Jacob</hi> fled away by ſtealth,<note place="margin">Chap. 31.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and made him (following) know</l>
                  <l>The wrong he did; and both good Friends,</l>
                  <l>after a chiding parted.</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Jacob</hi> in his Journey ſends</l>
                  <l>to pacifie hard-hearted</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eſau</hi> his Brother, who in Arms</l>
                  <l>was then againſt him bent;</l>
                  <l>But God prevented all the Harms,</l>
                  <l>and <hi>Eſau</hi> did relent.</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Jacob</hi> called <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 32.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>(for God had chang'd his Name</l>
                  <l>When he prevail'd at <hi>Peniel</hi>)</l>
                  <l>in peace to <hi>Shechem</hi> came.</l>
                  <l>Here <hi>Dinah</hi> did a gadding go</l>
                  <l>and to her ſelf brought Shame:</l>
                  <l>And to the <hi>Shechemites</hi> much wo,</l>
                  <l>and to her Brethren Blame.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>VI.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>THence up to <hi>Bethel</hi> had he word,</l>
                  <l>to go to pay his Vow</l>
                  <l>Of Holy Worſhip,<note place="margin">Chap. 35.</note> for the Lord</l>
                  <l>again to <hi>Canaan</hi> now;</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Padan Aram</hi> had him ſet;</l>
                  <l>where mightily he grew</l>
                  <l>In Family and Subſtance great:</l>
                  <l>his Sons Names here enſue.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Reuben, Dan, Levi, Simeon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iſſachar,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 29.30.</note> 
                     <hi>Napthalin,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aſer, Gad, Judah, Zebulon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Benjamin.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Theſe Twelve were Patriarchs, whoſe Seed,</l>
                  <l>ſtill multiplied more,</l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:154167:9"/>
                  <l>Even to thoſe Thouſands promiſed</l>
                  <l>ſo oft and long before.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Judah</hi> the Royal Line enjoy'd,</l>
                  <l>who for a Deed amiſs,</l>
                  <l>Had <hi>Tamar</hi>'s Life with fire deſtroy'd,</l>
                  <l>but that the Fault was his.</l>
                  <l>Young <hi>Joſeph Jacob</hi>'s Joy,<note place="margin">Chap. 37.</note> the reſt</l>
                  <l>ſtill ſtomached and ſpited,</l>
                  <l>Yet Hatred he deſerved leaſt,</l>
                  <l>had him his Brethren righted;</l>
                  <l>For Envy they conſpir'd to kill,</l>
                  <l>but <hi>Reuben</hi> did perſwade;</l>
                  <l>Yet ſecretly they did him ſell,</l>
                  <l>to Men of Merchants Trade;<note place="margin">Chap. 38.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who ſold him unto <hi>Potiphar,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>where though he lived chaſte,</l>
                  <l>And faithfully himſelf did bear,</l>
                  <l>yet was in Priſon caſt.<note place="margin">Chap. 39.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>But God beheld his Miſery,</l>
                  <l>and gave him Wiſdom great;</l>
                  <l>By which he was advanced high,</l>
                  <l>even next to <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Seat.</l>
                  <l>For when the King no Reſt could find,</l>
                  <l>of Dreams that him had paſt,<note place="margin">Chap. 41.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Th' ungrateful Butler then to mind</l>
                  <l>doth <hi>Joſeph</hi> call at laſt.</l>
                  <l>And then he was from Priſon ſent,</l>
                  <l>and ſet before the King;</l>
                  <l>Where he to <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s great Content,</l>
                  <l>Expounded every thing.</l>
                  <l>Beſides, he ſhew'd a ready way,</l>
                  <l>the Famine to withſtand,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Pharaoh</hi> lik'd, and then did lay</l>
                  <l>on him the Charge in hand.</l>
                  <l>So by him was Proviſion made,</l>
                  <l>againſt the time of Need:</l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:154167:10"/>
                  <l>Wherewith (to <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s gainful Trade)</l>
                  <l>all <hi>Aegypt</hi> he did feed.<note place="margin">Chap. 47. <hi>verſ.</hi> 14.17.19.</note>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>VII.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>OLD <hi>Jacob</hi> and his Sons alſo,<note place="margin">Chap. 42.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>were pinch'd with Penury,</l>
                  <l>Wherefore he charged them to go</l>
                  <l>and Food in <hi>Aegypt</hi> buy.</l>
                  <l>They went with Grief, and bought in Fear,</l>
                  <l>not dreaming of their Brother,</l>
                  <l>Nor did he Countenance them bear</l>
                  <l>more kind than any other;</l>
                  <l>Till when they came to him again,<note place="margin">Chap. 45.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Affection was ſo great,</l>
                  <l>He could no longer it contain,</l>
                  <l>within his Breaſt for heat.</l>
                  <l>With weeping Eye and joyful Tongue,</l>
                  <l>he then did plainly tell,</l>
                  <l>He was their Brother <hi>Joſeph,</hi> whom</l>
                  <l>to <hi>Aegypt</hi> they did ſell.</l>
                  <l>The Joy of either was ſo much,</l>
                  <l>that neither now could bear it;</l>
                  <l>Their ſobbing Paſſion was ſuch,</l>
                  <l>that <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Houſe did hear it.</l>
                  <l>Who underſtanding what they were,</l>
                  <l>commanded preſently,</l>
                  <l>With Charets, Horſe, and Furniture</l>
                  <l>for <hi>Jacob</hi> they ſhould hie.</l>
                  <l>So He with all his Family,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 2298. Chap. 46.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>came thither out of hand;</l>
                  <l>And welcomed moſt lovingly,</l>
                  <l>were plac'd in <hi>Goſhen</hi> Land.</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Goſhen</hi> Land did <hi>Jacob</hi> ſee</l>
                  <l>the fulneſs of his days,<note place="margin">Chap. 47.</note>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:154167:10"/>
                  <l>And in his Sons Proſperity,</l>
                  <l>his fill of earthly Joys.</l>
                  <l>But ſolemnly before his Death,</l>
                  <l>he bleſt his Sons each one:<note place="margin">Chap. 49.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Joſeph</hi> eke gave up the Breath,</l>
                  <l>e're many Years were gone.<note place="margin">Chap. 50.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Now when theſe Fathers both were dead,</l>
                  <l>and ſtill their Seed did grow:</l>
                  <l>There roſe a <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in his ſtead,</l>
                  <l>that did not <hi>Joſeph</hi> know.</l>
                  <l>He Tyrant-like with heavy Hand,</l>
                  <l>of Bondage preſt them down,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exodus.</hi> Chap. 1.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And gave the Midwives ſtrait command,</l>
                  <l>the Males to kill or drown.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>VIII.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>BOrn in theſe Flames was <hi>Moſes</hi> mild,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 2428.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and by God's Providence,</l>
                  <l>Though caſt in River Flags (poor Child)</l>
                  <l>yet was he freed thence;</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Daughter, who did take,<note place="margin">Chap. 2.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and keep him as her own;</l>
                  <l>Until he came to Man's Eſtate,</l>
                  <l>when fearing to be known,</l>
                  <l>For killing an <hi>Aegyptian;</hi> he</l>
                  <l>forſook the Court and fled:</l>
                  <l>And all this was by God's Decree,</l>
                  <l>whoſe Work muſt now be ſped.</l>
                  <l>For God had heard the grievous Cry,</l>
                  <l>of <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſore oppreſſed,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Moſes</hi> he meant to imploy</l>
                  <l>in having it redreſſed.<note place="margin">Chap. 3.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And called and ſent him away,<note place="margin">Chap. 4.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>to proud King <hi>Pharaoh;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:154167:11"/>
                  <l>Requiring him without delay</l>
                  <l>to let his People go.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did the Lord deſpiſe,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 2508.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and asked what was he?</l>
                  <l>Increaſing more and more their Cries,</l>
                  <l>by greater Cruelty.</l>
                  <l>The Lord to tame this Tyrant ſtout,<note place="margin">Chap. 5.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and his own Folk to right,</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Moſes</hi> ſendeth <hi>Aaron</hi> out,<note place="margin">Chap. 7.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>to make him know his Might.</l>
                  <l>They cauſed Blood, Frogs, Lice, and Flies,</l>
                  <l>with Murrain, Scabs, and Hail;</l>
                  <l>And Graſhoppers and darkened Skies,</l>
                  <l>all <hi>Aegypt</hi> to aſſail;<note place="margin">Chap. 8.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Excepting <hi>Goſhen</hi> Land,<note place="margin">Chap. 9.</note> where dwelt</l>
                  <l>God's People <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 10.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Heart did nothing melt,</l>
                  <l>for ſtill he did rebel.</l>
                  <l>Then was the Paſſover ordain'd,</l>
                  <l>and with the Paſchal Blood,<note place="margin">Chap. 12.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Poſts of all their Doors were ſtain'd,</l>
                  <l>for their Safegard and Good;</l>
                  <l>Leſt that the Angel paſſing by,</l>
                  <l>ſhould ſmite them with the reſt:</l>
                  <l>For he the Firſt-born did deſtroy,</l>
                  <l>of <hi>Aegypt</hi> Man and Beaſt:</l>
                  <l>Which Slaughter caus'd them dreadfully</l>
                  <l>at Midnight up to ſtart,</l>
                  <l>And to entreat with woful Cry,</l>
                  <l>all <hi>Iſrael</hi> to depart.</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Aegypt</hi> then they forced went,</l>
                  <l>with borrowed Jewels plenty,</l>
                  <l>When they in <hi>Aegypt</hi> Years had ſpent</l>
                  <l>four Hundred Ten and Twenty.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did repent the Deed,</l>
                  <l>and forthwith did not ſlack,</l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:154167:11"/>
                  <l>With Men and Chariots to make ſpeed</l>
                  <l>again to bring them back.</l>
                  <l>And to the Red-Sea them purſu'd,</l>
                  <l>they paſſed thorow dry,<note place="margin">Chap. 14.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>He followed with Courage proud,</l>
                  <l>but in the midſt did lie.</l>
                  <l>For God affrighted Man and Horſe,</l>
                  <l>and made his Chariots fall;</l>
                  <l>The Sea return'd with raging Force,</l>
                  <l>and drowned King and all.</l>
                  <l>Of this ſo ſtrange Deliverance,</l>
                  <l>was then a godly Song,<note place="margin">Chap. 15.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Recorded for Remembrance,</l>
                  <l>and ſo they march't along.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>IX.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>ABout this time (the learned Judge)</l>
                  <l>did patient <hi>Job</hi> endure,<note place="margin">Job.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>All Miſchiefs that the Devil's Grudge,</l>
                  <l>and Malice could procure</l>
                  <l>To Children, Servants, Goods, good Name,</l>
                  <l>to Body, and to his Mind;</l>
                  <l>By Fire, Sword, Whirlwinds, Botch and Blain,</l>
                  <l>by Wife and Friends unkind.</l>
                  <l>Who long and large Diſcourſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> had,</l>
                  <l>to prove him plagu'd for ſin,</l>
                  <l>Whereby they did Affliction add,</l>
                  <l>to Miſery he was in.</l>
                  <l>And to ſuch Paſſions did him drive,</l>
                  <l>'twixt hearts Deſpair and Hope,</l>
                  <l>That Fleſh and Spirit did ſtrongly ſtrive,</l>
                  <l>and ſcarce to Breath gave ſcope:</l>
                  <l>But God at laſt, Juſt <hi>Job</hi> commends,<note place="margin">Chap. 42.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and doubl'd his former Weal,</l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:154167:12"/>
                  <l>And check't his three cenſorious Friends,</l>
                  <l>but now to <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Lord their God in open ſight</l>
                  <l>directed them the way;<note place="margin">Chap. 13.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>By fiery Pillar in the Night,</l>
                  <l>and ſhady Cloud by Day.</l>
                  <l>With Angel's Food and Waters fine,</l>
                  <l>from Rocks that forced Stream,</l>
                  <l>He fill'd them,<note place="margin">Chap. 15.24.16.3.17.3.</note> yet they did repine</l>
                  <l>full oft, e're that they came</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Sinai;</hi> where the God of Might</l>
                  <l>in Glory did appear</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Iſrael</hi> trembled at the ſight:<note place="margin">Chap. 19.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>nor durſt,<note place="margin">Chap. 20.</note> nor might come near.</l>
                  <l>There did He give the Ten Commands,</l>
                  <l>and other Laws did Write,</l>
                  <l>For to contain them in the Bands</l>
                  <l>of Holineſs and Right.</l>
                  <l>There did he unto <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhow<note place="margin">Chap. 26.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>the Tabernacle's Frame;</l>
                  <l>In every Point he taught him how</l>
                  <l>to make and uſe the ſame.<note place="margin">Chap. 28.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>There made he choice of <hi>Levi</hi>'s Tribe,</l>
                  <l>the Prieſthood to attend.</l>
                  <l>And did their Duties all deſcribe</l>
                  <l>at large from End to End.</l>
                  <l>Mean while had <hi>Iſrael</hi> made a Calf,<note place="margin">Chap. 32.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and grievouſly offended;</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Moſes</hi> Zeal in God's behalf,</l>
                  <l>deſerves to be commended:</l>
                  <l>Who ſharply puniſh'd with the Sword,</l>
                  <l>about three Thouſand Men,</l>
                  <l>And earneſtly beſought the Lord,</l>
                  <l>to ſpare the Remnant then.</l>
                  <l>God granted it,<note place="margin">Chap. 33, 34.</note> and promiſed</l>
                  <l>his Angel ſhould (in Token</l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:154167:12"/>
                  <l>Of Love) them lead; and then he did</l>
                  <l>renew the Tables broken.</l>
                  <l>Full forty Days and forty Nights,</l>
                  <l>was <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Hill,</l>
                  <l>Recording what the Lord indites,</l>
                  <l>his Precepts, Laws and Will.</l>
                  <l>Familiarly and face to face,</l>
                  <l>and faſting from all Food,</l>
                  <l>He waited in that Holy Place:</l>
                  <l>and thence he came and ſtood</l>
                  <l>In preſs of People to recite</l>
                  <l>all that the Lord had ſaid;<note place="margin">Cap. 34.30.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>What time his Face did ſhine ſo bright,</l>
                  <l>as made them much afraid.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>X.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>WHen as the Tabernacle now,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 2510.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>was finiſhed and reared:</l>
                  <l>And with Appurtenances due,<note place="margin">Chap. 40.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>well furniſhed appeared.</l>
                  <l>Towards <hi>Canaan</hi> the promis'd Land,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Numbers.</hi> Chap. 10.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>that flow'd with Milk and Hony,</l>
                  <l>They marched forth Band after Band,</l>
                  <l>with ſtubborn Hearts and ſtony.</l>
                  <l>For by the way they ſoon forgot</l>
                  <l>Gods Mercy and his Power;</l>
                  <l>And car'd not how they him provok'd</l>
                  <l>to Anger every hour.</l>
                  <l>They long for Fleſh, they MANNA loath,<note place="margin">Chap. 11.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and back they will retire.</l>
                  <l>They fret at GOD and <hi>Moſes</hi> both,<note place="margin">Chap. 14.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>for croſſing their deſire:</l>
                  <l>Nor would they warned be, though they</l>
                  <l>his dreadful Judgments ſaw</l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:154167:13"/>
                  <l>On them inflicted day by day,</l>
                  <l>which liv'd not under Law.</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Korah,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>Dathan, Abiram,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>with thouſands more among,<note place="margin">Chap. 12.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nadab, Abihu, Miriam,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>and ſuch as Serpents ſtung.</l>
                  <l>Yet tempted they the Lord ſo long,</l>
                  <l>and with ſo high an hand;</l>
                  <l>That in his Wrath he ſwore, not one,</l>
                  <l>ſhould enter to the Land.</l>
                  <l>Save <hi>Joſhua</hi> and <hi>Caleb,</hi> who</l>
                  <l>returning with the Spies,<note place="margin">Chap. 14.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Affirm'd the Truth that they did know,</l>
                  <l>and croſs'd their Fellows Lies.</l>
                  <l>So wandred they in Wilderneſs,</l>
                  <l>the ſpace of forty Years;</l>
                  <l>Till all were dead that did tranſgreſs;</l>
                  <l>as by God's Book appears.<note place="margin">Chap. 26.64.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Their Sons he then did forward bring,</l>
                  <l>'gainſt all that kept them back,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Sihon, Og,</hi> and <hi>Moab</hi>'s King,</l>
                  <l>whoſe Name was <hi>Balaack.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who hired <hi>Balaam</hi> them to curſe,</l>
                  <l>and ſo thought to moleſt them;</l>
                  <l>But for himſelf it was much worſe,</l>
                  <l>for <hi>Balaam</hi> three times bleſt them:</l>
                  <l>He and thoſe two, and five Kings more,</l>
                  <l>which were of <hi>Midian,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 21.24.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Were in revenge of <hi>Baal-peor,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>ſubdued, ſpoiled, ſlain.<note place="margin">Chap. 22.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Here <hi>Reuben</hi>'s Tribe, and <hi>Gad</hi> alſo,<note place="margin">Chap. 31.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>their Heritage poſſeſt,</l>
                  <l>On promiſe they ſhould marching go</l>
                  <l>in Arms before the reſt.<note place="margin">Chap. 25.17, 18.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Here <hi>Moſes</hi> named every one</l>
                  <l>that ſhould the Land divide,<note place="margin">Chap. 32. Numb. 34.</note>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:154167:13"/>
                  <l>And gave a fit Poſſeſſion</l>
                  <l>unto each ſeveral Tribe.</l>
                  <l>And now muſt <hi>Moſes</hi> make an End,</l>
                  <l>as did his Fathers all:</l>
                  <l>Wherefore he did not time miſpend,<note place="margin">Deut. <hi>31.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>but preſently did call</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and gave him Charge,</l>
                  <l>the People to conduct,</l>
                  <l>Whom he by Sermons long and large,<note place="margin">Chap. 28.29.30.32.33.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>divinely did inſtruct.</l>
                  <l>Which with a ſweet and Swan-like Song,</l>
                  <l>in heavenly wiſe he ended;</l>
                  <l>And bleſt the Tribes each one along,</l>
                  <l>and forthwith he aſcended</l>
                  <l>Mount <hi>Nebo,</hi> unto <hi>Piſgah</hi> Top,<note place="margin">Chap. 34.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>whence as he did ſurvey,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Canaan</hi> Land, the earthly Hope,</l>
                  <l>God took his Soul away,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 2549.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>To Heavens reſt; and buried then,</l>
                  <l>his Body none know where,</l>
                  <l>When Peerleſs he amongſt all Men,</l>
                  <l>had lived ſixſcore Year:</l>
                  <l>And yet his Eye-ſight did not dim,</l>
                  <l>nor Natures Forces wither;</l>
                  <l>There <hi>Iſrael</hi> lamented him,</l>
                  <l>for thirty Days together.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>XI.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>THen did the Lord call <hi>Joſhua,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joſhua <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and bid him to be Strong,</l>
                  <l>And truſt in him who is his Stay,</l>
                  <l>and boldly go along.</l>
                  <l>So he the Captain ſends out Spies,<note place="margin">Chap. 2.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>whom <hi>Rahab</hi> ſafe did hide,</l>
                  <l>And they return'd in joyful wiſe,</l>
                  <l>which made them to provide</l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:154167:14"/>
                  <l>To paſs with ſpeed into the Land,</l>
                  <l>at <hi>Joſhua</hi> his Word,<note place="margin">Chap. 3.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Jordan</hi> Waters back did ſtand,</l>
                  <l>and Paſſage dry afford.</l>
                  <l>In midſt whereof in open view,<note place="margin">Chap. 4.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>they did a Pillar rear,</l>
                  <l>The Circumciſion they renew,<note place="margin">Chap. 5.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>the <hi>Manna</hi> ceaſed there.<note place="margin">Chap. 6.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then ſet they upon <hi>Jericho,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 7.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and alſo upon <hi>Ai.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But <hi>Achan</hi>'s Sin did work them wo,</l>
                  <l>and from the Conqueſt ſtay,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Gibeonites</hi> by Subtilty</l>
                  <l>were ſaved,<note place="margin">Chap. 9.</note> but the caſe</l>
                  <l>Of all the reſt, was for to die,</l>
                  <l>and give God's People place:</l>
                  <l>Who caſt them out, and did them kill,</l>
                  <l>with a victorious Hand,</l>
                  <l>For this the Sun and Moon ſtood ſtill,</l>
                  <l>at <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s Command.<note place="margin">Chap. 10.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>When he had now fully poſſeſt,</l>
                  <l>each ſeveral Tribe in order,</l>
                  <l>And given to all Content and Reſt</l>
                  <l>By Lot in every Border:</l>
                  <l>Religiouſly he did them preſs,</l>
                  <l>a Holy League to make,<note place="margin">Chap. 24.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>For him and his,<note place="margin">Chap. 25.</note> he did profeſs</l>
                  <l>none other God to take:</l>
                  <l>And them and theirs he did adjure</l>
                  <l>to fear this God for ay.</l>
                  <l>So having ſeal'd the Covenant ſure,</l>
                  <l>he paſs'd by Death away.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 2566.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Full ſoon had they the Lord forgot,</l>
                  <l>when <hi>Joſhua</hi> was dead,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Judah</hi> had the Charge and Lot</l>
                  <l>their Armies forth to lead,<note place="margin">Chap. 1</note>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:154167:14"/>
                  <l>But for their great Tranſgreſſions,</l>
                  <l>and League with <hi>Canaanite,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>God gave them to Oppreſſions,</l>
                  <l>of cruel Men of Might.</l>
                  <l>Who ſpoyl'd them without Mean or End,</l>
                  <l>and did them ſorely grieve,</l>
                  <l>Until their God did Judges ſend,<note place="margin">Chap. 2.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>their Grievance to relieve;</l>
                  <l>Againſt King <hi>Cuſhan</hi>'s Tyranny,<note place="margin">Chap. 3.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>ſtout <hi>Othniel</hi> raiſed he,</l>
                  <l>And when fat <hi>Eglon</hi> made them cry,</l>
                  <l>lame <hi>Ehud</hi> made them free.</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt <hi>Siſera</hi> of <hi>Canaan,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>did <hi>Deborah</hi> prevail,</l>
                  <l>Now <hi>Ruth</hi> obtain'd that honeſt Man,<note place="margin">Chap. 4.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>when nearer kin did fail,</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt <hi>Midian</hi> a mighty Hoſt,<note place="margin">Chap. 7.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>march'd Captain <hi>Gideon.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Bloody <hi>Abimelech</hi> did boaſt;<note place="margin">Chap. 9.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>he next would Reign or none,</l>
                  <l>The proud oppreſſing <hi>Ammonite,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 11.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>by <hi>Iphtah</hi> was ſubdued;</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Philiſtines</hi> for all their Spite,<note place="margin">Chap. 15.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>the Birth of <hi>Sampſon</hi> rued.</l>
                  <l>Whoſe matchleſs Strength miraculous,</l>
                  <l>was over-match'd by Guile,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Dalilah</hi> perfideous<note place="margin">Chap. 16.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>who wrought his Bane the while.</l>
                  <l>When none amongſt them rul'd as King,</l>
                  <l>each what he liſted did:</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Micah</hi> made a molten thing,<note place="margin">Chap. 17.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and it he worſhipped.</l>
                  <l>And at ſuch time, that hainous ſin,</l>
                  <l>upon the <hi>Levite</hi>'s Wife,</l>
                  <l>'Twixt <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Benjamin,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 19.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>coſt many a thouſands life.<note place="margin">Chap. 20.</note>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="section">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:154167:15"/>
                  <head>SECT. <hi>XII.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>ELI</hi> was Judge in <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>1</hi> Sam.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>when for his Sons lewd ways,</l>
                  <l>God threatned him by <hi>Samuel.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 3.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>that he a Scourge would raiſe:</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Samuel</hi> a righteous Man,</l>
                  <l>was laſt of all that judged,</l>
                  <l>And in his time the Kings began,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 2905.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>for then the people grudged;</l>
                  <l>And being male-content and ſad,<note place="margin">Chap. 8.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>would have a King to Reign,</l>
                  <l>O're them as other Nations had,</l>
                  <l>which was to <hi>Samuel</hi>'s pain.</l>
                  <l>But yet the Lord did them appoint,</l>
                  <l>a goodly Man and tall,<note place="margin">Chap. 9.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Samuel</hi> did him anoint</l>
                  <l>their King; his Name was <hi>Saul.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A Princely Mind God to him gave,</l>
                  <l>with Complements of Place;</l>
                  <l>And he with <hi>Jonathan</hi> did brave</l>
                  <l>His Enemies oft in Chaſe.<note place="margin">Chap. 13.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet God that him advanc'd ſo high,<note place="margin">Chap. 14.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>from Toyl and Aſſes Care;</l>
                  <l>He diſobey'd when fooliſhly,<note place="margin">Chap. 15.2.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>King <hi>Agag</hi> he did ſpare.<note place="margin">Chap. 15.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Therefore the Lord did him reject,</l>
                  <l>and little <hi>David</hi> choſe,</l>
                  <l>Anointed <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s King Elect,<note place="margin">Chap. 16.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>when he ſhould <hi>Saul</hi> Depoſe.</l>
                  <l>Now great <hi>Goliah</hi> plaid his Prize,<note place="margin">Chap. 17.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>but <hi>David</hi> knockt him down,</l>
                  <l>The People ſhout with joyful Cries,<note place="margin">Chap. 18.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and give him chief Renown.</l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:154167:15"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Saul</hi> bit the Lip at <hi>David</hi>'s Praiſe,</l>
                  <l>and hated him the more;</l>
                  <l>Yea, ſought his Life all manner ways,</l>
                  <l>and chas'd him like a Boar.<note place="margin">Chap. 19, 20.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>With Javelin and with threatning Sword,</l>
                  <l>with Troops of Horſe and Men,</l>
                  <l>From Houſe and Home, from Bed and Board,<note place="margin">Chap. 22, 23.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>from Deſart, Den to Den.</l>
                  <l>Forced he was himſelf to fain,</l>
                  <l>with <hi>Achiſh</hi> to be mad,<note place="margin">Chap. 21.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And for Defence to entertain</l>
                  <l>lewd Runnagates was glad.<note place="margin">Chap. 21.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>But <hi>Jonathan</hi> his faithful Friend,<note place="margin">Chap. 18.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>at no time did forſake him,<note place="margin">Chap. 19.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ever did him warning ſend,</l>
                  <l>when <hi>Saul</hi> us'd means to take him.<note place="margin">Chap. 20.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Although for it he did engage,</l>
                  <l>himſelf in Danger deep,</l>
                  <l>For ſuch was <hi>Saul</hi>'s ſuſpicious Rage,</l>
                  <l>none might his Counſel keep.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Abimelcch</hi> did give him Bread<note place="margin">Chap. 22.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>in his Neceſſity,</l>
                  <l>But for it he was murdered,<note place="margin">Chap. 22.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and all his Progeny.</l>
                  <l>Had <hi>David</hi> labour'd like for like,</l>
                  <l>his Enemy to repay,</l>
                  <l>He had both time and place to ſtrike,<note place="margin">Chap. 24.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and Soldiers bad him ſlay:<note place="margin">Chap. 26.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>When they were come in Cave alone,</l>
                  <l>when with him faſt aſleep,</l>
                  <l>But he the Lord's Anointed one,</l>
                  <l>from harm did ſafely keep.</l>
                  <l>And that he did both Mercy love,<note place="margin">Chap. 25.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and bloody Vengeance flee,</l>
                  <l>When churliſh <hi>Nabal</hi> did him move,</l>
                  <l>wiſe <hi>Abigail</hi> did ſee.</l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:154167:16"/>
                  <l>Now <hi>Saul</hi> with Envy almoſt pin'd,<note place="margin">Chap. 23.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and driven to diſtreſs,</l>
                  <l>Sought by a wretched Witch to find,</l>
                  <l>ſome Comfort and Redreſs.</l>
                  <l>Of which he fail'd, and in the field</l>
                  <l>as deſperately he fought.</l>
                  <l>His Sons were ſlain,<note place="margin">Chap. 31.</note> his Soldiers yield,</l>
                  <l>and gaſtly he beſought</l>
                  <l>His Armor-bearer him to kill;</l>
                  <l>but he the deed abhor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'d,</l>
                  <l>His own Heart blood he then did ſpill,</l>
                  <l>with his own Hand and Sword.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT.</hi> XIII.</head>
                  <l>THen <hi>David</hi> was proclaim'd and reign'd<note place="margin">
                        <hi>2</hi> Sam. Anno <hi>2945.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>in <hi>Hebron, Judah</hi>'s King:</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Iſhboſheth</hi> had <hi>Iſrael</hi> gain'd,</l>
                  <l>by <hi>Abners</hi> counſelling.</l>
                  <l>Long War was 'twixt the Houſes both,<note place="margin">Chap. 2.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>of <hi>David</hi> and of <hi>Saul,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Till <hi>Abner</hi> with his new King Wroth</l>
                  <l>to <hi>David</hi>'s ſide did fall.</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Abner</hi> and eke <hi>Iſhboſheth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 3.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>were ſlain by Villany:</l>
                  <l>But <hi>David</hi> did lament their death,</l>
                  <l>and Murderers all defie,</l>
                  <l>And being now eſtabliſhed,<note place="margin">Chap. 4.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>ſole King of all the Land:</l>
                  <l>And ſeeing each thing proſpered,<note place="margin">Chap. 5.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>that he did take in hand:</l>
                  <l>He ſolemnly doth think it fit,</l>
                  <l>to fetch the Ark more near him,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi>'s Death did hinder it,<note place="margin">Chap. 6.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>God's Judgment did ſo fear him.</l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:154167:16"/>
                  <l>Yet afterward he brought it on,</l>
                  <l>and purpoſed to rear,</l>
                  <l>A Houſe for God; but he would none,<note place="margin">Chap. 7.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>as <hi>Nathan</hi> made appear.</l>
                  <l>When he had all his Foes ſubdu'd,</l>
                  <l>and as a Monarch reign'd,</l>
                  <l>In Peace and Eaſe; ſee what enſu'd,</l>
                  <l>his upright Life was ſtain'd,<note place="margin">Chap. 11.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>With Murder and Adultery,<note place="margin">Chap. 12.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>whereof though he repented,</l>
                  <l>Yet was he puniſh'd diverſly</l>
                  <l>with haps to be lamented.</l>
                  <l>Firſt <hi>Abſalom</hi> ſhed <hi>Amnon</hi>'s Blood,<note place="margin">Chap. 13.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>for Inceſt then he roſe,</l>
                  <l>And like a Villain armed ſtood,<note place="margin">Chap. 15.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>his Father to depoſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Achitophel</hi> that crafty Wretch</l>
                  <l>had chief hand in this Matter,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Huſhai</hi> did him o're-reach,<note place="margin">Chap. 17.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>by Skill he had to flatter.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Shimei</hi> doth curſe, and rail,<note place="margin">Chap. 19.</note> and throw</l>
                  <l>ſtones at him as he fled,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sheba</hi> doth now Rebellion blow,</l>
                  <l>but for it loſt his Head.</l>
                  <l>The Peoples haſty numbering,<note place="margin">Chap. 24.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>coſt ſeventy thouſand Lives,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>1</hi> Kings.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And laſtly in his aged Years,<note place="margin">Chap. 1.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>the Son a Wanton bred,</l>
                  <l>Even <hi>Adoniah</hi> boldly tears</l>
                  <l>the Crown from off his Head.</l>
                  <l>This Prophet after God's own heart.</l>
                  <l>this ſweet Pſalm-ſinging Prince,</l>
                  <l>Did to his God at laſt depart,</l>
                  <l>with Peace of Conſcience.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:154167:17"/>
                  <head>SECT. <hi>IV.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>NExt him did <hi>Salomon</hi> his Son,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 2985.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>the Kingdoms Scepter ſway,</l>
                  <l>There never ſate on regal Throne,</l>
                  <l>his peer unto this day.</l>
                  <l>For Wealth,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>1</hi> Kings.</note> for State, for princely Port,</l>
                  <l>for Plenty and for Peace,</l>
                  <l>For Wiſdom rare, and great reſort;</l>
                  <l>which made his Fame increaſe.</l>
                  <l>Witneſs his Sentence in that Caſe,<note place="margin">Chap. 3.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>of Queans crying out of Wrongs,</l>
                  <l>His Purveiance,<note place="margin">Chap. 4.</note> his horſes Race,</l>
                  <l>his Proverbs, Writings, Songs:</l>
                  <l>Witneſs the Glorious Temple,<note place="margin">Chap. 6.</note> which</l>
                  <l>he built for God's Great Name;</l>
                  <l>The Carvings, Coverings, Hangings rich,</l>
                  <l>the Treaſures of the ſame.</l>
                  <l>Witneſs his Prayers that excel,<note place="margin">Chap. 8.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>for Words, for Zeal, for Fitneſs,</l>
                  <l>His Offerings wonderful and well</l>
                  <l>may that wiſe Queen bear witneſs.</l>
                  <l>Who wondring at the comon fame,</l>
                  <l>unto his Court reſorted,</l>
                  <l>To hear and ſee; and when ſhe came,<note place="margin">Chap. 107.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>loe! half was not reported.</l>
                  <l>Yet <hi>Solomon</hi> who had theſe Mines</l>
                  <l>of Wiſdom and of Treaſure,</l>
                  <l>By many Wives and Concubines,</l>
                  <l>and ſurfeiting in Pleaſure;</l>
                  <l>Was drawn from true Religion<note place="margin">Chap. 11.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and from Sincerity,</l>
                  <l>To wicked Superſtition,</l>
                  <l>and groſs Idolatry.</l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:154167:17"/>
                  <l>For which God's Judgment did begin,</l>
                  <l>his Kingdom rent in twain,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Judah</hi> alone and <hi>Benjamin,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>did to his Heirs remain.</l>
                  <l>The other Tribes, in number Ten,</l>
                  <l>from their Allegiance fell;</l>
                  <l>Set up a King, and nam'd him then,</l>
                  <l>the King of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>His Throne was at <hi>Samaria</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>on which he ruled them;</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Judah</hi>'s Seat Imperial,</l>
                  <l>was fair <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And there did <hi>Rehoboam</hi> reign,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 3015</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>when <hi>Shiſhak</hi> rob'd the Temple:<note place="margin">Chap. 12.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And next him, his Son <hi>Abiam,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 14.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>the worſe for his ill Example.</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Aſa,</hi> then <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 15.14.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>both good and holy Kings,</l>
                  <l>For reformation; ſaving that,<note place="margin">Chap. 22.43.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>they let alone ſome things.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>V.</hi> Kings of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>MEan time, in <hi>Iſrael, Nebat</hi>'s Son,<note place="margin">Chap. 12.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>King <hi>Jeroboam</hi> reigned.</l>
                  <l>Who firſt, at <hi>Bethel</hi> and at <hi>Dan,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>thoſe Calves and Prieſts ordained,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nadab</hi> his Son, King <hi>Baaſa,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 15.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>King <hi>Elah,</hi> and King <hi>Zimri,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Did for the Crown each other ſlay.</l>
                  <l>ſo likewiſe did King <hi>Omri:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 16.</note>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:154167:18"/>
                  <l>But his Son <hi>Ahab</hi> with his Wife,</l>
                  <l>that curſed <hi>Jezabel,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Exceeded in ungodly Life,</l>
                  <l>and to ſuch Fur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fell:</l>
                  <l>That good <hi>Eliah</hi> fled for fear,<note place="margin">Chap. 17.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>who was by Ravens fed;</l>
                  <l>Who rais'd the Widows Son moſt dear,</l>
                  <l>who laid <hi>Baal</hi>'s Prophets dead.</l>
                  <l>By whom King <hi>Ahab</hi> warning had;<note place="margin">Chap. 18.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>but words did naught prevail,</l>
                  <l>Nor Famine,nor yet <hi>Benhadad,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 2.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>who ſtrongly did aſſail</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Samaria:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 21.</note> yet for all that</l>
                  <l>he killed <hi>Naboth</hi> juſt,</l>
                  <l>And after got <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 22.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>to ſerve unto his Luſt.</l>
                  <l>For croſſing which, poor <hi>Micaiah,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 27.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>was in the Dungeon caſt,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Joſaphat</hi> in Battel ſaw,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verse</hi> 34.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>proud <hi>Ahab</hi> ſlain at laſt.</l>
                  <l>His Son took place when he was dead,</l>
                  <l>even wicked <hi>Ahaziah,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And after him was <hi>Joram</hi> Head,<note place="margin">Chap. 1.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>as then did good <hi>Eliah,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In fiery Chariot take his flight</l>
                  <l>to Heaven;<note place="margin">Chap. 2.</note> and in his place,</l>
                  <l>His Spirit did on <hi>Eliſha</hi> light,</l>
                  <l>with double Power and Grace.</l>
                  <l>To work great Miracles,<note place="margin">Chap. 4.</note> as by</l>
                  <l>the increaſed Oyl was proved,</l>
                  <l>And by <hi>Naaman</hi>'s Leproſie,<note place="margin">Chap. 5.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>which ſtrangely he removed.</l>
                  <l>And by the Plenty prophe<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ed,<note place="margin">Chap. 7.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>in ſtarv'd <hi>Samaria,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which the proud Prince that ſaid he ly'd,</l>
                  <l>to his ſmall comfort ſaw.</l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:154167:18"/>
                  <l>But <hi>Jehu</hi> did this <hi>Joram</hi> quell,</l>
                  <l>and reigned in his ſtead,</l>
                  <l>He ſlew alſo vile <hi>Jezebel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 9.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Baal</hi>'s Prieſts and <hi>Ahab</hi>'s Seed:<note place="margin">Chap. 10.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>His wicked Son <hi>Jehoahaz,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 13.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>ſucceeded;<note place="margin">Verſ. <hi>3.4.</hi>
                     </note> and the next</l>
                  <l>Was his Son <hi>Joaſh:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſ. <hi>25.</hi>
                     </note> either was</l>
                  <l>by <hi>Aram</hi>'s Armies vext.</l>
                  <l>Next <hi>Joaſh, Jeroboam</hi>'s Plea,</l>
                  <l>and Place was to ſucceed,</l>
                  <l>Now <hi>Jonas</hi> threatned <hi>Ninivy,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 14.23.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>but they repent with ſpeed.</l>
                  <l>Now did <hi>Hoſea</hi> take his Text,</l>
                  <l>and <hi>Amos</hi> Propheſie,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Jeroboam</hi> dead,<note place="margin">Chap. 15.</note> the next</l>
                  <l>was his Son <hi>Zachary.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whom <hi>Shallum</hi> ſlew in open fight<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 10.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and reigned in his ſtead,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Menahem</hi> did him requite,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 14.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and in his Seat ſucceed.</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Pekahiah, Men'hem</hi>'s Son,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 23.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>did wear the Crown until</l>
                  <l>His Captain <hi>Pekah</hi> ſeiz'd thereon,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 25.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and did his Sovereign kill.</l>
                  <l>Nor had this <hi>Pekah</hi> reigned long,</l>
                  <l>but he receiv'd his Doom,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hoſhea</hi> did revenge the Wrong,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 30.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and reigned in his room</l>
                  <l>In his time did <hi>Salmanazer,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 17.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>beſiege <hi>Samaria</hi> ſtrong,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>verſ.</hi> 6.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And took <hi>Hoſhea</hi> Priſoner,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 3265.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and led with him along,</l>
                  <l>All <hi>Iſrael</hi> into <hi>Syria,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>where they did ſtill remain,</l>
                  <l>And planted in <hi>Samaria,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>of his <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Train.</l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:154167:19"/>
                  <l>Whom God by Lyons did moleſt,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 25.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>for their Idolatries,</l>
                  <l>Which made them get an <hi>Hebrew</hi> Prieſt,</l>
                  <l>to teach them better ways.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>XVI.</hi> The Kings of <hi>Judah.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>THus leaving <hi>Iſrael</hi> diſpoſſeſt,</l>
                  <l>the courſe of Story brings</l>
                  <l>Us back to <hi>Judah,</hi> which was bleſt,</l>
                  <l>with more religious Kings.</l>
                  <l>There next unto <hi>Jehoſophat,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>did his Son <hi>Joram</hi> Reign,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Ahaziah,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. <hi>8.</hi>
                     </note> then upſtart</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Athalia</hi> who had ſlain</l>
                  <l>All the Kings Sons that ſhe could catch;<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>11.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>young <hi>Joaſh</hi> ſcap't alone,</l>
                  <l>By help of Friends, who made a Match,</l>
                  <l>to place him on his Throne.</l>
                  <l>He reign'd and did God's Houſe repair,</l>
                  <l>and left them when he died</l>
                  <l>King <hi>Amaſt,</hi> his hopeful Heir,</l>
                  <l>then <hi>Joel</hi> propheſied.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah Amaziah</hi>'s Son,<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>12.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>was ſtruck with Leproſie.<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>14.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>As he did reign,<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>15.</hi>
                     </note> and then begun</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iſaiah</hi>'s Propheſie.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jotham</hi> a Prince of God's beheſt,<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>16.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>ſucceeded next <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. <hi>18.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And after him <hi>Ahaz</hi> that beaſt,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 3260.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and then reign'd <hi>Hezekiah.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. <hi>18.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Againſt him proud <hi>Senacherib,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. <hi>19.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>ſent railing <hi>Rabſhekee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:154167:19"/>
                  <l>Who to his coſt was anſwered,</l>
                  <l>and caus'd with ſhame to flee.</l>
                  <l>Now was the Prophet <hi>Micak</hi> heard,</l>
                  <l>and <hi>Nahum:</hi> but we find,</l>
                  <l>That this good King from death reſerv'd<note place="margin">Chap. 20.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>towards <hi>Babel</hi> is too kind.</l>
                  <l>Next him, his Son <hi>Manaſſe</hi> reign'd,<note place="margin">Chap. 21.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>a wicked cruel King,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.12, 13.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Until he was in <hi>Babel</hi> chain'd:</l>
                  <l>but thence God did him bring.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ammon</hi> a man profanely vain,</l>
                  <l>his Father worſe way took,</l>
                  <l>And was by his own ſervants ſlain:</l>
                  <l>now preached <hi>Habakkuk.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.13.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then young <hi>Joſiah, Ammon</hi>'s Son,</l>
                  <l>a worthy Prince and zealous,</l>
                  <l>Made ſuch a Reformation<note place="margin">Chap. 12.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>as was and will be famous.</l>
                  <l>Now <hi>Jeremiah</hi> Trumpet-like</l>
                  <l>cries out; and <hi>Zephaniah:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But <hi>Necho</hi>'s men in Battel ſtrike,</l>
                  <l>and kill good King <hi>Joſiah.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 23.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>His Son <hi>Jehoahaz</hi> the Crown</l>
                  <l>obtain'd; but reign'd not long,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Pharaoh Necho</hi> put him down,</l>
                  <l>and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ain'd with Fetters ſtrong;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 24 1.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And plac'd his Brother in his room,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jehoiakim</hi> by name,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.4.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who <hi>Babel</hi>'s Vaſſal did become</l>
                  <l>for three Years ſpace with ſhame.</l>
                  <l>And then rebelling brought again<note place="margin">Anno 3389.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>great <hi>Nebuchadnezzar.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With all his huge and warlike Train:</l>
                  <l>who took him Priſoner,</l>
                  <l>And bound and carried him away,</l>
                  <l>with whom to <hi>Babylon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:154167:20"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ezekiel</hi> and <hi>Mordecai,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 3.16.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and <hi>Daniel</hi> are gone,</l>
                  <l>With other moe of Royal Seed,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 24.8.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>young <hi>Jechoni</hi> alone,<note place="margin">verſ. 10, 11.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Was left behind in's Fathers ſtead:</l>
                  <l>to ſit on <hi>Judah</hi>'s Throne;</l>
                  <l>Nor ſate he long but <hi>Babel</hi> doth,</l>
                  <l>his Souldiers ſtout command,</l>
                  <l>To fetch him and his Treaſure both,</l>
                  <l>and Chief Men of the Land.</l>
                  <l>His Unkle <hi>Zedekiah</hi> plac'd,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 3399.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>was in his room, and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>owned;</l>
                  <l>Who likewiſe did rebel at laſt,</l>
                  <l>but <hi>Babel</hi>'s King ſo frowned,<note place="margin">Chap. 24.17.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>That up againſt <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>the fourth time that he came,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>ver.</hi> 17.20.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>He by ſtrong Siege ſo ſtarved them,<note place="margin">Chap. 25.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>that Warriours fled with ſhame.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 3.5.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>King <hi>Zedekiah</hi> alſo fled,</l>
                  <l>but <hi>Chaldees</hi> quickly caught him,</l>
                  <l>And that due Judgment might be had,<note place="margin">Chap. 25.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>they unto <hi>Riblah</hi> brought him,</l>
                  <l>And ſlew his Sons before his face,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 6.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and then put out his Eyes,</l>
                  <l>And chained him with all Diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>that elſe they could deviſe.</l>
                  <l>And ſo to <hi>Babel</hi> they return,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno.</hi> 3400.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>with Priſoners and with Prey,</l>
                  <l>The Temple after that they burn,</l>
                  <l>and take all thence away.</l>
                  <l>Yea,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 8, 9.</note> burnt the Palace fair and rich,</l>
                  <l>which <hi>Solomon</hi> did build:</l>
                  <l>And all the goodly Houſes which</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> did yield.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="section">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:154167:20"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT.</hi> XVII.</head>
                  <l>BEing now at <hi>Babel</hi> faſt in Hold,<note place="margin">Dantel.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>the fineſt Wits were ſought,<note place="margin">Chap. 1.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or captive Children to be ſchool'd,</l>
                  <l>and <hi>Chaldee</hi> learning taught.</l>
                  <l>There <hi>Daniel</hi> among the reſt,</l>
                  <l>did to ſuch Ripeneſs come,</l>
                  <l>That when a Dream the King oppreſt,</l>
                  <l>and Wizzards all were dumb.</l>
                  <l>The Dream forgotten, he diſclos'd,<note place="margin">Chap. 2.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>which was an Image great<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 27.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of Metals different compos'd,</l>
                  <l>from head unto the feet.</l>
                  <l>This made the King much to admire,<note place="margin">Verſe <hi>4, 6.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>him and his fellows all,</l>
                  <l>Yet three were caſt into the fire,<note place="margin">Chap. 3.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>for that they would not fall</l>
                  <l>Before his Image hugely trim:</l>
                  <l>but fire could take no hold.</l>
                  <l>Another Dream then vexed him,</l>
                  <l>which <hi>Daniel</hi> did unfold;<note place="margin">Chap. 4.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And eke the ſtate of future Times,</l>
                  <l>Of Monarchs Crowns ſurpriſing.<note place="margin">Chap. 7, 8, 11, 12.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of Chriſt preciſely he divines</l>
                  <l>and of the Deads ariſing,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Babel</hi>'s King reſtored back,<note place="margin">Chap. 4.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>from Beaſts made better end,</l>
                  <l>Next him reign'd <hi>Evilmerodach,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>even <hi>Jeconiah</hi>'s Friend,</l>
                  <l>To him ſucceded <hi>Balſhazzar.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>who in his drunken Feaſt,</l>
                  <l>Did neither God nor's People ſpare,<note place="margin">Chap. 25.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>for Blaſphemy and Jeſt;</l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:154167:21"/>
                  <l>Till fingers writing on a wall,</l>
                  <l>dazling his very ſight,</l>
                  <l>Did ſo his Countenance appall,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 8.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>was never man ſo fright.</l>
                  <l>This Writing <hi>Daniel</hi> did expound</l>
                  <l>unto his further pain,</l>
                  <l>For even that night he was uncrown'd,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 30.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and by <hi>Darius</hi> ſlain.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT.</hi> XVIII.</head>
                  <l>WHen now full ſeventy Years were ſpent,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 3458.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>in their Captivity,</l>
                  <l>King <hi>Cyrus</hi> Proclamation ſent,</l>
                  <l>for their Delivery.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> doth then retire,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ezra.</hi> Chap. 1.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>with all the Temples Treaſure.</l>
                  <l>And full Commiſſion to repair</l>
                  <l>the Ruins at their pleaſure.</l>
                  <l>But crafty Foes did plot apace,</l>
                  <l>the Lord's Work to withſtand,<note place="margin">Chap. 4.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>By flattering Speech unto their face.</l>
                  <l>and Letters under hand;</l>
                  <l>Yea, <hi>Haman</hi>'s Hatred cankered,</l>
                  <l>had clean deſtroy'd them all,</l>
                  <l>Had not Queen <hi>Eſther</hi> ventured,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſther.</hi> Chap. 3.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and ſav'd them from the Thrall,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Haggai,</hi> alſo <hi>Zachary,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ezra.</hi> Chap. 5.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>the ſlackneſs do reprove;</l>
                  <l>And ſhortly after <hi>Malachi,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>their lack of Zeal and Love.</l>
                  <l>At laſt the Temple finiſhed,</l>
                  <l>was by <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Nehemi</hi> with Letters ſped,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nehemia.</hi> Chap. 2.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>to build the Walls as well.</l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:154167:21"/>
                  <l>Which he perform'd for all the hate</l>
                  <l>of Enemies prophane,<note place="margin">Chap. 6.15.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tobiah,</hi> wicked <hi>Sanballat,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>and worſe <hi>Samaritane.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And then he kept a ſolemn Feaſt,</l>
                  <l>whereat the Law was read,<note place="margin">Chap. 4. <hi>Verſe</hi> 1, 2. Chap. 8.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſeal'd a Covenant with the reſt,</l>
                  <l>their God to ſerve and dread.</l>
                  <l>Next Kings and Dukes, the <hi>Maccabees,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 10.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>(as Stories do recite)</l>
                  <l>Did rule them: but the Monarchies,</l>
                  <l>ſtill top't them by their Might.<note place="margin">1 <hi>The</hi> Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>In ſuch Subjection did they mourn,<note place="margin">2 <hi>The</hi> Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>four hundred Years, and odd,</l>
                  <l>Until <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> Chriſt was born,<note place="margin">3 <hi>The</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>true Man and very God.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="list_of_dukes">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:154167:22"/>
               <head>The Dukes of <hi>David</hi>'s Stock, after the Return out of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Jeconias,</hi> Jer. 52.</item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Shelathiel,</hi> Hag. 1.</item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Zorobabel.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 <hi>Reza.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5 <hi>Joanna.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6 <hi>Judas Hyrcanus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7 <hi>Joſeph Primus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8 <hi>Abner Semei.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>9 <hi>Eli Mattathia.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>10 <hi>Azar Mahat.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>11 <hi>Nagid Artaxad.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>12 <hi>Haggai Eli.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>13 <hi>Maſlot Naum.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>14 <hi>Amos Syrac.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>15 <hi>Mattathia Siloath.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>16 <hi>Joſeph Secundus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>17 <hi>Janna Hyrcanus.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>This <hi>Janna</hi> was ſlain by <hi>Antiochus Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes</hi> King of <hi>Syria,</hi> who tyrannized over them, until <hi>Mattathias</hi> the high Prieſt arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and encouraged his Sons againſt him; who drave him out of the Countrey, and ſucceſſively reigned in his room.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="list_of_princes_and_kings">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:154167:22"/>
               <head>The Princes and Kings of the <hi>Family</hi> of the <hi>Maccabees.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Judas Macchabeus</hi> the Son of <hi>Mattathias,</hi> reigned—5 years.</item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Jonathan</hi> an other Son—19 years.</item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Simon</hi> a third Son—8 years.</item>
                  <item>4 <hi>Johannes Hyrcanus</hi>—31 years.</item>
                  <item>5 <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> his Son—1 year.</item>
                  <item>6 <hi>Alexander Janneus</hi>—27 years.</item>
                  <item>7 <hi>Alexandra</hi> his Wife—9 years.</item>
                  <item>8 <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> her Son ſucceeded, but <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulus</hi> his younger Brother rebelled and made War againſt him: wherefore <hi>Hyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus</hi> ſent Embaſſadors to <hi>Pompey</hi> the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Captain for Aid. <hi>Pompey</hi> came to <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> ſubdued the Rebels, gave the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Prieſthood to <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> and carried <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> with his two Sons <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> and <hi>Antigonus</hi> Captives towards <hi>Rome. Alexander</hi> eſcaped by the way, and returned, and got part of <hi>Galilee;</hi> but was taken again by <hi>Gabinius,</hi> and afterward put to death at <hi>Antioch</hi> by <hi>Scipio</hi> the Father-in-law of <hi>Pompey. Antigonus</hi> was ſet at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> after the Battel between him and <hi>Pompey.</hi> But coming into <hi>Jewry,</hi> he dealt cruelly with his old Uncle <hi>Hyrca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> the high Prieſt, cutting off his Ears, and baniſhing him into <hi>Parthia,</hi> for which Cauſe he was taken again, and Executed at <hi>Antioch,</hi> by <hi>Antony, Herod</hi>'s Lieutenant in <hi>Jewry.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:154167:23"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Herod</hi> alſo ſent for <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> out of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia,</hi> and put him to death, and ſo came the Family of the <hi>Maccabees</hi> fully to an end, and the Kingdom of <hi>Jewry</hi> was eſtabliſhed to <hi>Herod</hi> and his Heirs.</p>
               <div type="lineage">
                  <head>The Poſterity of <hi>Herod.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE Kingdom or Province of <hi>Jewry</hi> was given by <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> to <hi>Antipater</hi> of <hi>Idumea</hi> the Father of <hi>Herod,</hi> in recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of the faithful and good Service which he did in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> in the time of his Wars and Dangers there.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Herod</hi> the Son of <hi>Antipater,</hi> called <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> the Great, was made King by the Senate of <hi>Rome,</hi> and reigned 37 years. He pulled down the Temple, that was built after the Captivity, and built another after the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s, wonderful rich and ſtately. He put to death <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> his Sons, upon ſuſpicion of Treaſon: in his thirtieth Year was Chriſt Jeſus born.</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Archelaus</hi> another of his Sons ruled <hi>Judea</hi> nine years.</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Herod Antipas</hi> another Son, governed <hi>Galile;</hi> he beheaded <hi>John Baptiſt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. <hi>Philip</hi> another Son, governed <hi>Ituria.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. <hi>Herod Agrippa,</hi> the Son of <hi>Ariſtobulus,</hi> who killed <hi>James,</hi> and was eaten up of Worms, <hi>Acts cap.</hi> 12.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Agrippa</hi> his Son (mentioned with <hi>Bernice</hi> his Siſter, <hi>Acts</hi> 25.) being a Child, was carried into <hi>Syria,</hi> and the <hi>Romans</hi> took the Government of <hi>Jewry</hi> again into their own hands, as in former time.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="timeline">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:154167:23"/>
               <head>A Brief Supputation of the Years and Times from the Creation of the World,<note place="margin">The Age of the World</note> unto the Birth of Chriſt: Collected out of <hi>Junius,</hi> according to the <hi>Scriptures.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <label>Gen. 5.</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>ADam</hi> being 130 years old be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat <hi>Seth</hi>— 130</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Seth</hi> at 105 years old begat <hi>Enoſh</hi>— 235</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Enoſh</hi> at 90 begat <hi>Kenan</hi>— 325</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Kenan</hi> at 70 begat <hi>Mahalaleel</hi>— 395</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Mahalaleel</hi> at 65 begat <hi>Jared</hi>— 460</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Jared</hi> at 162 begat <hi>Enoch</hi>— 622</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Enoch</hi> at 65 begat <hi>Methuſhelah</hi>— 687</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Methuſelah</hi> at 187 begat <hi>Lamech</hi>— 874</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Lamech</hi> at 182 begat <hi>Noah</hi>— 1056</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Noah</hi> at 502 begat <hi>Shem</hi>— 1558</item>
                        <item>In his 500 year he begat <hi>Japhet,</hi> for thus <hi>Junius</hi> readeth it out of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> (Brother to <hi>Japhet</hi> the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,) <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.21.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Shem</hi> at 100 years old old begat <hi>Arpachſhad</hi> — 1658</item>
                        <item>This being two years after the Flood, (which came in <hi>Noah</hi>'s ſix hundreth year) it followeth that he was begotten in the five hundred
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:154167:24"/>and ſecond year of <hi>Noah, Gen.</hi> 11. <hi>verſe</hi> 10.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <label>Gen. 11</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>1693 —<hi>Arpachſhad</hi> at 35 begat <hi>Shelah</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>1723 —<hi>Shelah</hi> at 30 begat <hi>Heber.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>1759 —<hi>Heber</hi> at 35 begat <hi>Peleg.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>1787 —<hi>Peleg</hi> at 30 begat <hi>Reu.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>1819 —<hi>Reu</hi> at 32 begat <hi>Serug.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>1849 —<hi>Serug</hi> at 30 begat <hi>Nahor.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>1878 —<hi>Nahor</hi> at 29 begat <hi>Terah.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Terah</hi> at 70 began to beget Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren (ſaith <hi>Junius</hi>) and at 130 begat <hi>Abram</hi>—</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>This plainly appeareth, for <hi>Terah</hi> was 205 years old when he died in <hi>Haran, Gen.</hi> 11.32. and <hi>Abram</hi> going out of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran,</hi> ſhortly after was but 75. <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.4. Now deduct the Son's Age out of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and there remaineth 130. to <hi>Terah</hi> at <hi>Abram</hi>'s Birth.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>2108 <hi>Abraham</hi> at 100 years begat <hi>Iſaac.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2168 <hi>Iſaac</hi> at 60 begat <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Jacob.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2293 <hi>Jacob</hi> being 130 years old, goeth down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Aegypt, Geneſis</hi> 47.9.</item>
                  <item>2315 <hi>Jacob</hi> died 17 years after his coming into <hi>Aegypt, Gen.</hi> 47.28.</item>
                  <item>2368 <hi>Joſeph</hi> died 53 years after his Father <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, Gen.</hi> 50.</item>
                  <item>2428 <hi>Moſes</hi> was born 60 years after the Death of <hi>Joſeph.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2508 <hi>Moſes</hi> was 80 years old when he ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Pharaoh, Exod.</hi> 7.7.</item>
                  <item>2510 The Tabernacle was reared the ſecond year after, <hi>Exod.</hi> 40.17.</item>
                  <item>2549 <hi>Moſes</hi> died 40 years after the departure out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and 39 after the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle erected, <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.3.</item>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:154167:24"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Joſhua</hi> died 17 years after <hi>Moſes.</hi> 2566</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Othniel</hi> died 40 years after <hi>Joſhua.</hi> 2606</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ehud</hi> died 80 years after <hi>Othniel.</hi> 2686</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Deborah</hi> died 40 years after <hi>Ehud.</hi> 2726</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gideon</hi> died 40 years after <hi>Deborah.</hi> 2766</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Abimelech</hi> uſurped 3 years. 2769</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tola</hi> died 23 years after <hi>Abimelech.</hi> 2792</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Jair</hi> died 22 years after <hi>Tola.</hi> 2814</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iphtah</hi> died 6 years after <hi>Jair.</hi> 2820</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ibzan</hi> died 7 years after <hi>Iphtah.</hi> 2827</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Elon</hi> died 10 years after <hi>Ibzan.</hi> 2837</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Abdon</hi> died 8 years after <hi>Elon.</hi> 2845</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sampſon</hi> died 20 years after <hi>Abdon.</hi> 2805</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Eli</hi> died 40 years after <hi>Sampſon.</hi> 2905</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Samuel</hi> ſucceeded to the time of <hi>Saul.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Saul</hi> began his Reign, and reigned alone, and with <hi>Samuel</hi> 40 years. 2905</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>David</hi> reigned 40 years. 2945</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Solomon</hi> reigned 40 years. 2985</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rehoboam</hi> reigned 17 years. 3025</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Abiam</hi> reigned 3 years. 3042</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aſa</hi> reigned 41 years. 3045</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> reigned 25 years. 3086</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Jehoram</hi> reigned 4 years after his Fathers Death; having been made <hi>Viceroy</hi> twice in his Father's life-time. Firſt in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteenth year, as appeareth, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.51. compared with 2 <hi>King.</hi> 1.17. 3111</item>
                  <item>And again, in his 22 year, as appeareth 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.1. compared with <hi>cap.</hi> 8.16</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Athaliah</hi> reigned 6. 3115</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Joaſh</hi> reigned 39 year. 3121</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Amaſiah</hi> reigned 29 years. 3160</item>
               </list>
               <p>In his ſeventeenth year (or the fourth of <hi>Jeroboam</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael</hi>) there was a Conſpiracy againſt him, and he fled to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:154167:25"/>
                  <hi>Lachiſh,</hi> and lived there a baniſhed Man 11 years. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> his Son being in the mean ſpace made King by the common people, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 14.21. See <hi>Junius</hi> his Note on the place. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> reigned 52 years.</p>
               <p>3177 About this time began the <hi>Greek Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piads,</hi> by which they made a Computation of all memorable Matters. It was a Game inſtituted by <hi>Hercules,</hi> on the Hill <hi>Olympus</hi> in <hi>Greece,</hi> which was held in the beginning of every fifth Year, and continued five days with great Solemnity, and Concourſe out of all Countries.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>3229 —<hi>Jotham</hi> reigned alone 15 years.</item>
                  <item>3244 —<hi>Ahaz</hi> reigned 16 years.</item>
                  <item>3260 —<hi>Hezekiah</hi> reigned 29 years.</item>
                  <item>3289 —<hi>Manaſſe</hi> reigned 55 years.</item>
                  <item>3344 —<hi>Ammon</hi> reigned 2 years.</item>
                  <item>3346 —<hi>Joſiah</hi> reigned 31 years.</item>
                  <item>3377 —<hi>Jehoiakim</hi> reigned 11 years.</item>
                  <item>3388 <hi>Jeconiah</hi> reigned three months, and was carried captive to <hi>Babel,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.</item>
                  <item>3399 —<hi>Zedekiah</hi> reigned 11 years.</item>
                  <item>3425 From <hi>Zedekiah</hi> to the Exaltation of <hi>Jehoia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kim,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 25.30.—26 years.</item>
               </list>
               <div type="summary">
                  <head>In Sum.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>From the Creation of <hi>Adam,</hi> to the Flood, are — 1656 years.</item>
                     <item>From the Flood to the death of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> are — 910 years.</item>
                     <item>From <hi>Joſhua</hi> to the death of <hi>Eli,</hi> are — 339 years.</item>
                     <item>From <hi>Eli</hi> to the Deportation of <hi>Jeconias,</hi> are — 473 years.</item>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:154167:25"/>
                     <item>From the Captivity of <hi>Jeconias</hi> to the Edict of <hi>Cyrus</hi> for their Deliverance (promiſed <hi>Jerem.</hi> 25.11. and performed in the firſt year of his Reign) are—70 years.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Anno</hi> 3458.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>From the Edict of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> beginneth the firſt of <hi>Daniel</hi>'s 70 weeks.</item>
                     <item>Theſe 70 weeks are to be expounded as the Sabbaths, or Weeks in the year of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile, <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.8. and continue in the whole — 490 yeare.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Theſe are divided by <hi>Gabriel</hi> the Angel into three parts, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.25.</p>
                  <p>Firſt he appointeth 7 Weeks, or a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath of Weeks, or a Jubile of 49 years, for the building of the Temple, and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the pure Worſhip of God.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, he appointeth 62 Weeks (which contain 434 years) for repairing of the City, and building the Walls. And theſe begin with the Commiſſion of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> (from <hi>Darius, Artaxerzes Longimanus</hi>) <hi>Neh.</hi> 2.9. and reach unto the laſt Week in which <hi>Meſſiah</hi> began to preach.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, he ſpeaketh of the laſt Week, and divideth it into two parts.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In the firſt part, and midſt of it, or in the fourth year, he ſaith that <hi>Meſſiah</hi> ſhall aboliſh the Sacrifice and Oblation: namely by offering up himſelf once for all, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.14. Which is more plainly expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.26. where he is ſaid to be cut off, or Crucified and delivered to Death. But nothing to him, that is, Death ſhall not prevail over him, but that he ſhall make good his Judgments upon a rebellious and gainſaying People. For it is ſaid, <hi>(He ſhall
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:154167:26"/>deſtroy the City, and the Holy Things.)</hi> or the Temple; and that with ſuch Severity, as if a flood of Wrath and Judgment ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up all.</p>
                  <p>Theſe 69 weeks and a half week con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain 487 years, which fall out juſt, by this Account</p>
                  <p>From the Edict of <hi>Cyrus</hi> to the Re-edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of the Temple,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ezra</hi> 6.15.7.12 <hi>Anno</hi> 3507.</note> and the return of the People, by the Command of <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> the whole time of <hi>Ezra</hi> his Story, are 49 years.</p>
                  <p>From the Temple finiſhed,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 3577.</note> to the Repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the City <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the end of <hi>Arſanes</hi> his Reign; the time of <hi>Nehemia</hi>'s Story, — 70 years.</p>
                  <p>From thence to the Death of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, are — 12 years.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Alexander</hi> died in the firſt year of the 114 <hi>Olympiad,</hi> and Chriſt was Crucified the laſt year of the 202 <hi>Olympiad.</hi> Which 89 <hi>Olympiads</hi> contain 356 years, and ſo is the Sum 487 fully made up.</p>
                  <p>The latter part,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 3945.</note> or other half of the week, is referred unto the <hi>Revelation</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament, cap.</hi> 11.3. where it is ſaid that the two Witneſſes ſhall Propheſie, 1260 days, or 42 months; which make up three years and a half: and ſo the full number of the 70 weeks.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:154167:26"/>
               <head>THE SECOND PART</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>I.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>OF <hi>Abram</hi>'s Seed and <hi>David</hi>'s Line</l>
                  <l>directly Chriſt deſcended:<note place="margin">Mat. 1. Luke 3.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>So have th' <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> Divine</l>
                  <l>by Scripture left commended.</l>
                  <l>Before him was an Herald ſent,</l>
                  <l>his Coming to proclaim:</l>
                  <l>Who cry'd in Wilderneſs, <hi>Repent,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 3.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>the Paths of God make plain.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>His Clothing was of Hair and Skin,</l>
                  <l>his Meat of no great Coſt,</l>
                  <l>And for reproving <hi>Herod</hi>'s ſin,<note place="margin">Mat. 14.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>his Head at laſt he loſt.</l>
                  <l>This was that <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt whoſe</l>
                  <l>Birth, Name and Office high,</l>
                  <l>The Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> did diſcloſe,<note place="margin">Luke 1.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>to his Father <hi>Zachary.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who thought it not to be believ'd,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 18.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and for it was ſtruck dumb,</l>
                  <l>Till old <hi>Elizabeth</hi> had Conceiv'd</l>
                  <l>and all to paſs was come.</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Mary</hi> eke of <hi>Nazaret,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 26.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>a Virgin Pure and Chaſt,</l>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:154167:27"/>
                  <l>With Salutation high and great,</l>
                  <l>this <hi>Gabriel</hi> did haſte.</l>
                  <l>Shewing that ſhe muſt Mother be,</l>
                  <l>God's dear Son forth to bring,</l>
                  <l>The Holy Ghoſt by high Decree,</l>
                  <l>her overſhadowing.</l>
                  <l>And at that very time betroth't</l>
                  <l>ſhe was to <hi>Joſeph</hi> Juſt:</l>
                  <l>When being found with Child,<note place="margin">Mat. 1.</note> he thought</l>
                  <l>that part with her he muſt.</l>
                  <l>But then an Angel warned him</l>
                  <l>by Dream to keep her ſtill,</l>
                  <l>For that ſhe had Conceiv'd within,</l>
                  <l>was God's own Work and Will,</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Bethlem</hi> ſhe was brought to Bed,</l>
                  <l>and <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> was Born,</l>
                  <l>And in a Manger ſwaddeled,<note place="margin">Luke 2.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>as one caſt out to ſcorn:</l>
                  <l>But heavenly Angels made him known</l>
                  <l>to Shepherds, forthwith they</l>
                  <l>Found out the Babe, as had been ſhown,</l>
                  <l>and publiſh't it with Joy.</l>
                  <l>Then was he Circumcis'd and Nam'd,</l>
                  <l>and (as the Law indented)</l>
                  <l>Brought to the Temple, fitly fram'd,</l>
                  <l>and to the Lord preſented.</l>
                  <l>Where Holy <hi>Simeon</hi> did him bleſs,</l>
                  <l>and with a Song embrace him:</l>
                  <l>And aged <hi>Ann,</hi> a Propheteſs,</l>
                  <l>preach't publickly to grace him.</l>
                  <l>Yea, Eaſtern Wiſemen came from far,</l>
                  <l>and did rich Treaſures bring,</l>
                  <l>Directed by a ſpecial Star,</l>
                  <l>to find out <hi>Judah</hi>'s King.</l>
                  <l>Who worſhipped, and warned were</l>
                  <l>by God in their return,</l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:154167:27"/>
                  <l>To take good heed, and not come near,</l>
                  <l>King <hi>Herod</hi> who did burn</l>
                  <l>With Wrath and Envy 'gainſt this new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born</l>
                  <l>greater King of <hi>Jury,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And being mocked ſent and ſlew</l>
                  <l>the Infants in a Fury.</l>
                  <l>But God to <hi>Joſeph</hi> warning gave,</l>
                  <l>to <hi>Aegypt</hi> thence to fly,</l>
                  <l>The Babe and Mother, there to ſave,</l>
                  <l>from <hi>Herod</hi>'s Cruelty.</l>
                  <l>King <hi>Herod</hi> dead, then haſted he</l>
                  <l>to <hi>Iſrael</hi> again:</l>
                  <l>But turn'd aſide to <hi>Galilee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>becauſe his Son did reign.</l>
                  <l>And all this was for to acquite</l>
                  <l>the Propheſies of old,</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Aegypt</hi> and a <hi>Nazarite,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>to come he was foretold.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>II.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>AT twelve Years old with Doctors he</l>
                     <l>in Temple doth diſpute;<note place="margin">Luke 2.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Hearers all amaſed be,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Verſ.</hi> 46.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>his Mother is alſo mute.</l>
                     <l>At thirty Years he was by <hi>John</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Baptiz'd in <hi>Jordan,</hi> and</l>
                     <l>Proclaimed God's Beloved Son,<note place="margin">Mat. 3.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>while Heavens open ſtand.</l>
                     <l>To Wilderneſs then was he led,<note place="margin">Mat. 4.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>and faſted forty Days:</l>
                     <l>The Devil there he vanquiſhed,</l>
                     <l>though tempted many ways.</l>
                     <l>And ſo, his Miniſtry of Weight,</l>
                     <l>he cloſely ſets about:</l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:154167:28"/>
                     <l>He chuſeth Twelve Apoſtles ſtraight,<note place="margin">Mat. 10. Luke 10.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>and alſo ſends them out:</l>
                     <l>And ſeventy more, by two and two,</l>
                     <l>he ſent with like Command,</l>
                     <l>To Preach, to Heal, and to Subdue</l>
                     <l>the Devils that did withſtand.</l>
                     <l>To quicken them, the more, he did</l>
                     <l>part of his Glory ſhew,</l>
                     <l>Being on the Mount transfigured</l>
                     <l>into an heavenly Hew.<note place="margin">Mat. 17.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nor was he idle,<note place="margin">John 2.14. Luke 19.45.</note> but did purge,</l>
                     <l>the Temple firſt and laſt,</l>
                     <l>And ſtill he did Repentance urge</l>
                     <l>as up and down he paſt.</l>
                     <l>At <hi>Nazaret</hi> he took his Text</l>
                     <l>in <hi>Eſay</hi>'s Propheſie:<note place="margin">Matt. 13.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whence hardly ſcaping,<note place="margin">Luke 4.</note> he did next</l>
                     <l>to <hi>Capernaum</hi> hie.</l>
                     <l>There Satan ſhew'd his diſcontent,</l>
                     <l>but ſtrongly was caſt out.</l>
                     <l>Unto the great Aſtoniſhment,</l>
                     <l>of all that ſtood about.</l>
                     <l>He taught a Doctor of the Law,<note place="margin">Matt. 4. John 3.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>a Leſſon new and ſtrange.</l>
                     <l>In the Woman of <hi>Samaria</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>he wrought a wondrous Change.<note place="margin">John 4. Matt. 5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>He made a Sermon on the Mount,</l>
                     <l>moſt heavenly and large.</l>
                     <l>Nine bleſſed Sorts he did recount,</l>
                     <l>and preſs the Preachers Charge.</l>
                     <l>The Laws of God he likewiſe there</l>
                     <l>did perfectly Expound,</l>
                     <l>He taught them how to pray,<note place="margin">Matt. 6.</note> and where</l>
                     <l>and gave them Precepts ſound.</l>
                     <l>For practice of True Piety,</l>
                     <l>and taking heed alſo,</l>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:154167:28"/>
                     <l>Of Cares and of Hypocriſie,</l>
                     <l>and many Duties moe,</l>
                     <l>Which uttered were in Parable,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Matt. 6.</hi> verſe <hi>26.</hi> Chriſt's Parables.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>or in plain Speeches brought,</l>
                     <l>Each Word and every Syllable,</l>
                     <l>with Power upon them wrought.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>By Builders. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 7.24. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.22. <hi>Luke</hi> 14.28.</l>
                     <l>Bridegroom. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 9.15. <hi>cap.</hi> 22.2. <hi>cap.</hi> 25.1.</l>
                     <l>Brides. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 6.26. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.29. <hi>cap.</hi> 23.37.</l>
                     <l>And Bread. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 15.26. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.9. <hi>John</hi> 6.48.</l>
                     <l>By Beaſts. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 8.20. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.6, 15. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.34.</l>
                     <l>Thieves. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 24.43. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.30. <hi>John</hi> 10.1.</l>
                     <l>Spirits unclean. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 12.27. <hi>&amp; verſe</hi> 47.</l>
                     <l>By Servants. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 6.24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.31. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24.46. <hi>Lu.</hi> 17.7.</l>
                     <l>Shepherds. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 18.12. <hi>Jo.</hi> 10.11. <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.36. <hi>&amp;</hi> 25.33.</l>
                     <l>Salt. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Luke</hi> 14.34. <hi>Mark</hi> 9.49.</l>
                     <l>And Seeds. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 13.3. <hi>cap.</hi> 17.10. <hi>cap.</hi> 13.24. <hi>&amp; v.</hi> 31.</l>
                     <l>By Net. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 13.47.</l>
                     <l>New Cloth and Wine. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 9.16. <hi>&amp; verſe</hi> 17.</l>
                     <l>By Light. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 5.14, 15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 73. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.22. <hi>John</hi> 8.12.</l>
                     <l>And Leven. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 13.33. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.6.</l>
                     <l>Feaſts. (<hi>Luke</hi> 14. <hi>verſe</hi> 12. <hi>verſe</hi> 8. <hi>verſe</hi> 16.</l>
                     <l>And Friends. (<hi>Luke</hi> 11.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.9.</l>
                     <l>By rich Men. (<hi>Luke</hi> 12.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.1.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.10.</l>
                     <l>Trees. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 7.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.33. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21.19. — <hi>&amp;</hi> 26.32. <hi>Luke</hi> 13.6.</l>
                     <l>And Treaſure. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 6.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.35. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.34.52. — <hi>&amp;</hi> 25.14.</l>
                     <l>By Children. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 11.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24.28. <hi>Lu.</hi> 15.11.</l>
                     <l>Women. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 12.50. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24.41. <hi>Luke</hi> 15.8.</l>
                     <l>Ways. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 7.13. <hi>John</hi> 14.6.</l>
                     <l>And Vines. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 21.33. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20. 1 <hi>John</hi> 15.1.</l>
                     <l>he taught them out of meaſure,</l>
                     <l>Deep Myſteries which long lay hid,</l>
                     <l>which he from Heaven brought</l>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:154167:29"/>
                     <l>And by ſtrange Miracles he did</l>
                     <l>confirm what he had taught.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>III.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>AT <hi>Cana</hi> he did at their need,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chriſt's Miracles.</hi> John 2. Matt. 14.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>turn Water into Wine,</l>
                  <l>And with five Loaves five Thouſand fed.</l>
                  <l>by his great Power Divine.</l>
                  <l>Another time four thouſand Men,<note place="margin">Matt. 15.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>with ſeven Loaves he filled.</l>
                  <l>He walked on the Sea,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.26. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.32.</note> and when</l>
                  <l>it rag'd, the Waves he ſtilled.</l>
                  <l>Cood ſight he gave to many blind,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20. <hi>Mark</hi> 8. <hi>John</hi> 9.</l>
                  <l>And Speech unto the dumb,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.32. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.22. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.32.</l>
                  <l>The lame, their Limbs do firmly find,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.10. <hi>Luke</hi> 13.11. <hi>John</hi> 5.8.</l>
                  <l>The deaf to Hearing come. <hi>Mark</hi> 7.32.</l>
                  <l>He healed Sickneſſes long bred.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.6.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.26.</l>
                  <l>Even foul and leprous Evils,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.3. <hi>Luke</hi> 17.12.</l>
                  <l>Yea more, he raiſed up the dead,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 7.12. <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.21. <hi>Mark</hi> 5.41.</l>
                  <l>And diſpoſſeſt the Devils.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.29. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.31. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.15. <hi>Mark</hi> 9.20.</l>
                  <l>Yet for all this he was not free,</l>
                  <l>but had Controllers many,</l>
                  <l>To carp and quarrel, pry and ſee,</l>
                  <l>if fault they could find any.<note place="margin">Mat. 26.2. Cap. 22.35. John 8.6.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Among the reſt the Sadducees,</l>
                  <l>with thoſe of <hi>Herod</hi>'s Train,</l>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:154167:29"/>
                  <l>The Scribes alſo and Phariſees</l>
                  <l>did ever more remain</l>
                  <l>His deadly Enemies, and did ſeek</l>
                  <l>to trap him in a Snare,</l>
                  <l>By crafty Queſtions, rough or meek,</l>
                  <l>what way, they did not care.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22.16.35. <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.11. <hi>Luke</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>— 10.25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.15.</l>
                  <l>But yet his hour was not come,</l>
                  <l>he ſtill preach't painfully,</l>
                  <l>And them bequeath'd a heavy Doom,<note place="margin">Matt. 23.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>for their Hypocriſie.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> her fearful State,<note place="margin">Matt. 24.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>he did with Grief foreſay,</l>
                  <l>The manner eke he did relate,</l>
                  <l>of the laſt Judgment-day.</l>
                  <l>But comforteth his choſen Ones,</l>
                  <l>with ſpiritual Conſolation,</l>
                  <l>As ſweetly may be ſeen in <hi>John</hi>'s</l>
                  <l>divine and long Relation.<note place="margin">John 14.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, 16, 17.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſo to <hi>Bethani</hi> he went,</l>
                  <l>where <hi>Simon</hi> him received;</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Mary</hi>'s Box upon him ſpent,<note place="margin">Matt. 26.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>diſſembling <hi>Judas</hi> grieved.</l>
                  <l>Then was the Paſſover prepar'd,</l>
                  <l>and <hi>Judas</hi> pointed out,</l>
                  <l>A Traitor to his Sovereign Lord:</l>
                  <l>and then he went about,</l>
                  <l>A work of Grace, a Sacrament,</l>
                  <l>a Supper to ordain,</l>
                  <l>A Seal of Love, a Teſtament,</l>
                  <l>that ſhould with his remain:</l>
                  <l>Thence went he to <hi>Mount Olivet</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>as was his uſe to pray,</l>
                  <l>Of ſcattering and of Scandal great,</l>
                  <l>he told them by the way.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:154167:30"/>
                  <head>SECT. <hi>IV.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>MEan while did Prieſts a Council call,</l>
                  <l>and did his Death conſpire,</l>
                  <l>They hired <hi>Judas</hi> in their Hall,</l>
                  <l>to work them their deſire:</l>
                  <l>Who promis'd to effect it ſo,</l>
                  <l>as that they ſhould not miſs;</l>
                  <l>With him their Captain, on they go,</l>
                  <l>their Token is a Kiſs.</l>
                  <l>As Chriſt in Garden praying was,</l>
                  <l>with Sighs and Groans moſt deep,</l>
                  <l>That fearful Cup to have it paſs,</l>
                  <l>the reſt oppreſt with ſleep:</l>
                  <l>In comes this rude and bloody Rout,</l>
                  <l>which <hi>Peter</hi> could not bear,</l>
                  <l>But drew his Sword and laid about,</l>
                  <l>and cut off <hi>Malchus</hi> Ear;</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Jeſus</hi> heal'd,<note place="margin">John 18.</note> and to their Will,</l>
                  <l>he yields though at his words,</l>
                  <l>They firſt gave ground and backward fell,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 6.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>though arm'd with Clubs and Swords.</l>
                  <l>The poor Apoſtles fly for fear,<note place="margin">Matt. 26.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>yea,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 56.</note> 
                     <hi>Peter</hi> thrice denied</l>
                  <l>His Maſter;<note place="margin">Chap. 27.</note> 
                     <hi>Judas</hi> doth deſpair</l>
                  <l>and hang'd himſelf and died.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 5.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>To high Prieſts-Hall they led him then,</l>
                  <l>and witneſs falſe ſuborned:</l>
                  <l>Spat in his Face,<note place="margin">Matt. 14.</note> and by their Men,</l>
                  <l>he was both beat and ſcorned.</l>
                  <l>Then did they him to <hi>Pilate</hi> ſend,<note place="margin">Matt. 27.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>where being found moſt clear,</l>
                  <l>To free him <hi>Pilate</hi> did intend,</l>
                  <l>and that the <hi>Jews</hi> did fear.</l>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:154167:30"/>
                  <l>And then began with Might and Main,</l>
                  <l>tumultuouſly to cry,</l>
                  <l>To let looſe <hi>Barabbas</hi> again,<note place="margin">Luke, 23.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and <hi>Chriſt</hi> to Crucifie.</l>
                  <l>Nor were the common Souldiers ſlack,<note place="margin">Matt. 27.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>to ſtrip him of his Weed,</l>
                  <l>A Scarlet Robe put on his Back,</l>
                  <l>and in his Hand a Reed.</l>
                  <l>And on his Head a Crown of Thorns,</l>
                  <l>then do they bow the Knee.</l>
                  <l>So, on him having ſpent their Scorns,</l>
                  <l>to <hi>Golgotha</hi> goes he,</l>
                  <l>They forced <hi>Simon</hi> by the way,</l>
                  <l>to help him bear his Croſs,</l>
                  <l>On which they did his Hands diſplay,</l>
                  <l>and nail, without remorſe:</l>
                  <l>Betwixt two Thieves they did him place,</l>
                  <l>and gave him Gall to drink,</l>
                  <l>They ſhew'd him all the vile diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>that Heart of Man could think:</l>
                  <l>Thieves, Phariſees, Prieſts, Paſſers by,<note place="margin">Mat. 27.38. Luke 23.34.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>all ſcoff and wag and Head,</l>
                  <l>All which he bare moſt patiently,</l>
                  <l>till all was finiſhed.</l>
                  <l>Then rent the Temple vail in twain,<note place="margin">Matt. 27.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>the Stones did cleave aſunder.</l>
                  <l>The Graves did ope, the dead again,</l>
                  <l>did riſe and walk with wonder.</l>
                  <l>The Earth lay trembling, and the Sun</l>
                  <l>abaſh't in darkneſs bode,</l>
                  <l>And then cry'd the Centurion,<note place="margin">Luke 23. Matt. 27.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>this was the Son of God.</l>
                  <l>His Body <hi>Joſeph</hi> did take down,</l>
                  <l>and lap in Linnen ſweet,</l>
                  <l>And in a new Tomb of his own,</l>
                  <l>did bury it as was meet.</l>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:154167:31"/>
                  <l>The Prieſts his Reſurrection fear'd</l>
                  <l>and therefore took good heed,</l>
                  <l>To keep him ſure with Watch and Ward,</l>
                  <l>and ſeal'd the Tomb with ſpeed.</l>
                  <l>But he the third Day did ariſe,<note place="margin">Matt. 28.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>as he had them foretold,</l>
                  <l>Then did the Prieſts, to publiſh lies,</l>
                  <l>corrupt the Guard with Gold.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>V.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>CHRIST being Riſen, did appear,</l>
                  <l>and charged the Eleven,</l>
                  <l>To Preach and Baptize every where,</l>
                  <l>by warranty from Heaven.</l>
                  <l>And purpoſing to furniſh them,</l>
                  <l>with Knowledge, Tongues and Art,</l>
                  <l>He bids them from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 1</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>in no wiſe to depart.</l>
                  <l>Till Promiſes performed were;</l>
                  <l>which ſaid; out of their ſight,</l>
                  <l>A Cloud to Heaven did him bear,</l>
                  <l>and two in Garments white,</l>
                  <l>Did check their gazing, and fore-ſhow</l>
                  <l>his coming back again.</l>
                  <l>Then to the City back they go,</l>
                  <l>where all as one remain</l>
                  <l>In Prayer and Requeſt to God:</l>
                  <l>there <hi>Pe er</hi> doth propoſe</l>
                  <l>To fill the number that was od;</l>
                  <l>the Lot <hi>Matthias</hi> choſe.</l>
                  <l>Upon the day of Pentecoſt,<note place="margin">Chap 2.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>in cloven Tongues like fire,</l>
                  <l>From Heaven high the Holy Ghoſt,</l>
                  <l>th' Apoſtles did inſpire.</l>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:154167:31"/>
                  <l>Then did they in ſtrange Tongues report</l>
                  <l>the wondrous Works of God,</l>
                  <l>Aſtoniſh't was therewith each ſort</l>
                  <l>of Strangers that abode</l>
                  <l>Within the City; others mook't,</l>
                  <l>but <hi>Peter</hi> took their part,</l>
                  <l>And by his Sermon ſoundly knock't,<note place="margin">Chap. 3.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>three Thouſand at the Heart.</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>John</hi> and he together joyn'd,<note place="margin">Chap. 3.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and heal'd the Creeple lame,</l>
                  <l>To Priſon though they were confin'd,</l>
                  <l>yet were they freed for ſhame.</l>
                  <l>To preach the Truth they were all bold,<note place="margin">Chap. 4.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and many Wonders wrought,</l>
                  <l>Nor would they be by Prieſts controll'd</l>
                  <l>though oft in danger brought.</l>
                  <l>For they in ſuffering did rejoyce,</l>
                  <l>and God ſent Help at need;</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Hypocrites</hi> at <hi>Peter</hi>'s voice,<note place="margin">Chap. 5.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>were ſuddenly ſtruck dead.</l>
                  <l>Then did they for poor Widows moan,<note place="margin">Chap. 6.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>ſeven honeſt Deacons chuſe,</l>
                  <l>Of which was bleſſed <hi>Stephen</hi> one,<note place="margin">Chap. 7.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>who martyr'd was by <hi>Jews.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Saul</hi> was conſenting to this deed,<note place="margin">Chap. 8</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and with his threatning ſore,</l>
                  <l>Scattered th' Apoſtles far and wide,</l>
                  <l>but God's Word grew the more.</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Philip</hi> in <hi>Samaria,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>with Power it was taught,</l>
                  <l>And into <hi>Aethiopia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'twas by th' <hi>Eunuch</hi> brought:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Damaſcus</hi> ſuccoured many a Saint;</l>
                  <l>which <hi>Saul</hi> no ſooner found,</l>
                  <l>But to the Prieſts he made Complaint,</l>
                  <l>for power to bring them bound.</l>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:154167:32"/>
                  <l>And quickly ſped: but ſee a change,</l>
                  <l>this hot blood-ſucking <hi>Saul,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By Viſion heavenly and ſtrange,</l>
                  <l>became bold-preaching <hi>Paul.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>At <hi>Joppa Peter</hi> rais'd the dead,<note place="margin">Chap. 10.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and did the Goſpel plant,</l>
                  <l>And in <hi>Caeſarea</hi> he ſped,</l>
                  <l>Captain <hi>Cornelius</hi> want.</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Antioch</hi> the Word was ſpread,<note place="margin">Chap. 11.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>by Preachers there diſperſt,</l>
                  <l>Who truly following Chriſt the Head,</l>
                  <l>were there call'd Chriſtians firſt.</l>
                  <l>Now <hi>Herod</hi> ſtormed:<note place="margin">Chap. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>James</hi> was ſlain,</l>
                  <l>and <hi>Peter</hi> priſoned faſt:</l>
                  <l>An Angel looſed <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chain,</l>
                  <l>Worms eat the King at laſt.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>VI.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>BUt <hi>Paul</hi> (call'd <hi>Saul</hi>) ſurpaſt them all,</l>
                  <l>in Patience and Pains-taking:</l>
                  <l>To preach the Word to great and ſmall,</l>
                  <l>he evermore was waking;</l>
                  <l>By Day, by Night, by Sea, by Land,</l>
                  <l>by Pen, and eke by Mouth,</l>
                  <l>Though Perils great were oft at hand,</l>
                  <l>yet publiſh't he the Truth:</l>
                  <l>Four ſpecial Journeys did he make,</l>
                  <l>in leſſer <hi>Aſia</hi> one,</l>
                  <l>And twice he croſs'd the<note n="*" place="margin">or <hi>Mare</hi> Aegeum.</note> 
                     <hi>Grecian</hi> Lake,</l>
                  <l>and then to <hi>Rome</hi> is gone.</l>
                  <l>With him alſo the Holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Chap. 13.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>ſet <hi>Barnabas</hi> apart.</l>
                  <l>Their Charge was in the heathen Coaſt,</l>
                  <l>the <hi>Gentiles</hi> to convert.</l>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:154167:32"/>
                  <l>From <hi>Antioch</hi> they firſt ſet out,</l>
                  <l>and unto <hi>Paphos</hi> came:</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Sergius</hi> to the Faith was brought,</l>
                  <l>and <hi>Elimas</hi> to ſhame,</l>
                  <l>Then in <hi>Piſidia</hi> did he preach,</l>
                  <l>and in <hi>Iconion,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He ſtayed long, and ſtill did teach,<note place="margin">Chap. 14.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>till Stirs cauſe him be gone.</l>
                  <l>Thence did he unto <hi>Lyſtra</hi> flee,<note place="margin">Chap. 14.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and there he heal'd the Lame,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 11.19.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>For which, a god, then ſton'd, but he,</l>
                  <l>thence back to <hi>Antioch</hi> came.</l>
                  <l>Th' Apoſtles at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 15.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>did now a Council call,</l>
                  <l>A falſe Opinion to condemn</l>
                  <l>which did the Church befal.</l>
                  <l>A ſecond Journey they intend,</l>
                  <l>but <hi>John Mark</hi> doth divide them:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Barnabas</hi> doth to <hi>Cyprus</hi> bend,</l>
                  <l>but <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Sylas</hi> hide them.</l>
                  <l>Through <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Silicia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>and with them they conſort</l>
                  <l>Young <hi>Timothy,</hi> of whom they have,<note place="margin">Chap. 16.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>a ſpecial good Report.</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Macedonia</hi> by night,</l>
                  <l>they called were and ſent,</l>
                  <l>The Devil there gives God his Right,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 17.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>there <hi>Lydia</hi> doth repent,</l>
                  <l>And eke the Jaylor: forthwith they</l>
                  <l>to <hi>Theſſalonica</hi> moved,</l>
                  <l>Thence to <hi>Berea,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 17.</note> where they joy</l>
                  <l>to ſee their preaching proved.</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Athens</hi> next did <hi>Paul</hi> diſpute,<note place="margin">Chap. 18.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and thence to <hi>Corinth</hi> came,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 3.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where he with <hi>Aquila</hi> did ſute,</l>
                  <l>and <hi>Criſpus</hi> Chriſtian frame.</l>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:154167:33"/>
                  <l>There <hi>Gallio</hi> doth ſhift his hand</l>
                  <l>though hardly <hi>Jews</hi> complain,</l>
                  <l>So back he goes to <hi>Syria</hi> and</l>
                  <l>to <hi>Antioch</hi> again.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 22.</note>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>VII.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>THen did he his third Journey haſt,</l>
                  <l>towards <hi>Graecia</hi> once more.</l>
                  <l>Through leſſer <hi>Aſia</hi> he paſt,</l>
                  <l>as he had done before.</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Epheſus</hi> he made ſome ſtay,</l>
                  <l>for there the Word prevailed,</l>
                  <l>There was <hi>Apollo</hi> ſhew'd the way,<note place="margin">Chap. 19.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and there <hi>Demetrius</hi> railed.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Philippi</hi> laſt he viſited,</l>
                  <l>and thence he ſailed back,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Troas;</hi> where he rais'd the dead</l>
                  <l>and after did not ſlack,</l>
                  <l>Unto <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to come;</l>
                  <l>yet ſailing thither-ward,<note place="margin">Chap. 20.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>The planted Churches all and ſome</l>
                  <l>to ſee, he had regard.</l>
                  <l>(For in his Journies as he went)</l>
                  <l>he preach'd and Churches planted,</l>
                  <l>And coming back, was diligent</l>
                  <l>for to ſupply what wanted.</l>
                  <l>He did Confirm them, and Ordain</l>
                  <l>Elders in every place,</l>
                  <l>With Faſt and Prayer, and then again</l>
                  <l>commend them to God's Grace.</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Ptolemais</hi> one day they bide,</l>
                  <l>and to <hi>Ceſarea</hi> walked,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Philip</hi>'s Daughters propheſi'd,</l>
                  <l>and <hi>Agabus</hi> fore-talked</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Paul</hi> his Bands and Sufferings great,<note place="margin">Chap. 21.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>but he was naught diſmai'd</l>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:154167:33"/>
                  <l>To ſuffer Death (though they intreat)</l>
                  <l>he ready was he ſaid:</l>
                  <l>So, up he went, and being there</l>
                  <l>made to them full relation;</l>
                  <l>With Praiſe to God they gladly hear</l>
                  <l>the <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſtrange vocation.</l>
                  <l>To pleaſe the <hi>Jews,</hi> they did adviſe</l>
                  <l>to purifie him there,</l>
                  <l>But in the Temple Stirs ariſe,</l>
                  <l>and like to coſt him dear.</l>
                  <l>Had not the Captain ceas'd the ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>and by his great Friendſhip,</l>
                  <l>Account he rendred of his Life,</l>
                  <l>and Faith, and ſcap't the Whip.</l>
                  <l>Then was he brought before the Prieſt,<note place="margin">Chap. 22.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and ſmitten, but the Fray,</l>
                  <l>'Twixt <hi>Sadducees, Scribes,</hi> and the reſt,</l>
                  <l>hindred the Plea that day.</l>
                  <l>Then was he unto <hi>Felix</hi> ſent,<note place="margin">Chap. 23.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>his Anſwer there to make,</l>
                  <l>Thither alſo the high Prieſt went,</l>
                  <l>and did <hi>Tertullus</hi> take:</l>
                  <l>The Orator, to plead their Caſe;<note place="margin">Chap. 24.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>but nothing yet they gain'd.</l>
                  <l>Till <hi>Feſtus</hi> came in <hi>Felix</hi> place,</l>
                  <l>before him being raign'd,</l>
                  <l>And King <hi>Agrippa:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 25.</note> he thinks well</l>
                  <l>to yield him up in Bands:</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Caeſar</hi> did appeal,<note place="margin">Chap. 26.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and ſo eſcap'd their Hands.</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Italy</hi> then was he bound,</l>
                  <l>with a Centurions Guard:</l>
                  <l>But Perils great on Sea they found,<note place="margin">Chap. 27.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>the like hath ſcarce been heard.</l>
                  <l>Toſt up and down the Ship at laſt,<note place="margin">Chap. 27.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>ſtuck faſt within the Sand:</l>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:154167:34"/>
                  <l>And there was all to pieces daſht:</l>
                  <l>yet all came ſafe to Land,</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Malta:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap 28.</note> where the Viper quick,</l>
                  <l>maid the <hi>Barbarians</hi> quail,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Paul</hi> ſcap'd the Danger, heal'd their ſick,</l>
                  <l>and thence to <hi>Rome</hi> did ſail.</l>
                  <l>Where he arriving was by <hi>Jews,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>both met and entertained,</l>
                  <l>He told the Brethren joyful News,</l>
                  <l>and two Years there remained</l>
                  <l>In his own Houſe, but guarded by</l>
                  <l>a Souldier of the Train,</l>
                  <l>Until that <hi>Nero</hi> cruelly,</l>
                  <l>did cauſe him to be ſlain.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>VIII.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>AS <hi>Paul</hi> in preaching got the Prize,</l>
                  <l>ſo <hi>John</hi> did mount moſt high,</l>
                  <l>God's Holy hidden Myſteries,<note place="margin">Revelation.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>and Secrets to deſcry.</l>
                  <l>Who, in the Spirit, on the Lord's Day,</l>
                  <l>in <hi>Patmos</hi> baniſhed,</l>
                  <l>Wrote Words divine, and bleſt are they</l>
                  <l>which underſtand and read.</l>
                  <l>Firſt, to the ſeven Churches he</l>
                  <l>ſends healthful Salutation,<note place="margin">Chap. 4.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then ſets he out God's Majeſty</l>
                  <l>and Book of <hi>Revelation.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 5.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>But ſeven Seals this Book did cloſe,</l>
                  <l>and none could be found out</l>
                  <l>Worthy the Seals for to unloſe,</l>
                  <l>till came the Lyon ſtout</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Judah</hi>'s Tribe, the <hi>Lamb once</hi> ſlain,</l>
                  <l>he every Seal did open,</l>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:154167:34"/>
                  <l>And each Seal drew as in a Chain,</l>
                  <l>ſome ſtrange and ſpecial Token.</l>
                  <l>The firſt reveal'd a Horſe milk white,</l>
                  <l>(the Goſpel's Speed and Power)</l>
                  <l>The ſecond red,<note place="margin">Chap. 6.</note> and did delight</l>
                  <l>by bloodſhed to devour.</l>
                  <l>The third was black, and notice had</l>
                  <l>of Plague and Famine fell,</l>
                  <l>The fourth Horſe then full pale and ſad,</l>
                  <l>did <hi>Antichriſt</hi> foretel,</l>
                  <l>The fifth Seal open'd did bewray,</l>
                  <l>Saints Souls that had been killed;</l>
                  <l>Which under Heavens Altar lay,</l>
                  <l>till were the Number filled.</l>
                  <l>The ſixth unſealed, there were ſeen</l>
                  <l>moſt fearful Signs and Wonders:<note place="margin">Chap. 7.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>But God ſeal'd (ſpite of <hi>Satan</hi>'s ſpleen)</l>
                  <l>twelve times twelve thouſand Numbers:</l>
                  <l>Laſt, opening the ſeventh Seal,</l>
                  <l>loe Angels ſeven attend,<note place="margin">Chap. 8.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Before the Lord,<note place="margin">Chap. 11.15.</note> and they reveal</l>
                  <l>the World's State to the end.<note place="margin">Chap. 8.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Theſe Angels ſeven Trumpets had,</l>
                  <l>but each in order blows,</l>
                  <l>And for the World would be ſo bad,</l>
                  <l>denounced nought but Woes.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>IX.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>THen mightily with glorious Look,<note place="margin">Chap. 10.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Chriſt Jeſus is revealed,</l>
                  <l>And in his Hand a <hi>little Book,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>but open and unſealed.</l>
                  <l>This Book Saint <hi>John</hi> did take and ate,</l>
                  <l>and it th' Eſtate contained,</l>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:154167:35"/>
                  <l>Of God's Church preſent, and of that</l>
                  <l>her Glory which remained.</l>
                  <l>For preſent ſtate, ſhe never wants,</l>
                  <l>the preaching of God's Spell,</l>
                  <l>Two Candleſticks,<note place="margin">Chap. 11.</note> two Olive Plants,</l>
                  <l>two Witneſſes this tell.</l>
                  <l>And though ſhe cloath'd be with the Sun,</l>
                  <l>and on the Moon do tread;</l>
                  <l>Yet Wars againſt her are begun,</l>
                  <l>by Foes that make her dread:</l>
                  <l>And firſt the <hi>Dragon</hi> caus'd her flie,<note place="margin">Chap. 12.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>into God's Wilderneſs,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Michael</hi> from Heaven high,</l>
                  <l>his Fury doth repreſs.</l>
                  <l>Then did a Beaſt make War on her,<note place="margin">Chap. 13.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>ſeven headed, and ten horned.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And after him there did appear</l>
                  <l>another Beaſt adorned.</l>
                  <l>Like to the Lamb, with Horns but two</l>
                  <l>yet <hi>Dragon</hi>-like he ſpake,</l>
                  <l>And did what the firſt Beaſt could do,</l>
                  <l>compelling all to take</l>
                  <l>His Mark upon their Fore-head: yet</l>
                  <l>the <hi>Lamb</hi> had thouſands ſtill,</l>
                  <l>On Earth,<note place="margin">Chap. 14.</note> that him with Praiſes greet,</l>
                  <l>ſigned to do his Will.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>X.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>NOr doth he <hi>Babylon</hi> forget,<note place="margin">Chap. 14.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>th' Idolatrous drunken Whore,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Three</hi> Angels he againſt her ſet,</l>
                  <l>and after <hi>ſeven</hi> more;</l>
                  <l>The firſt, by preaching to deſcry.</l>
                  <l>the next, to ſhew her Fall,</l>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:154167:35"/>
                  <l>The third doth Torments notifie,</l>
                  <l>bequeath'd her Lovers all.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>ſeven,</hi> ſeven Vials had,<note place="margin">Chap. 19.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>full of the Wrath of God,</l>
                  <l>Which they pour'd out as they were bad</l>
                  <l>on all the Earth abroad.<note place="margin">Chap. 16.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Unto the ruin of the Beaſt,</l>
                  <l>and of the Whore of <hi>Rome:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 17.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>That golden purple <hi>Antichriſt;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>for this her heavy Doom,</l>
                  <l>Kings of the Earth, and Merchants proud,<note place="margin">Chap. 18.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>take up a Lamentation:</l>
                  <l>But Holy Saints ſing Praiſes loud,</l>
                  <l>for Churches Preſervation,</l>
                  <l>Unto the Conquerous of Fame,,<note place="margin">Chap. 19.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>that cloath'd is with the Word,</l>
                  <l>And bears on <hi>Thigh,</hi> a <hi>mighty Name.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>and in <hi>in his Mouth a Sword:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who ſummoned triumphantly,</l>
                  <l>to his victorious Feaſt,</l>
                  <l>The Fowls that by mid-heaven flie,</l>
                  <l>as for his Foe, the Beaſt,</l>
                  <l>He with the <hi>Prophet</hi> falſe were caſt</l>
                  <l>into the Brimſtone Lake:</l>
                  <l>The Sword devoured all the reſt,</l>
                  <l>that part with him did take.</l>
                  <l>And then the Devil that <hi>Dragon</hi> ſtout,<note place="margin">Chap. 20.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>that <hi>Serpent</hi> old (once chained,</l>
                  <l>A thouſand years, and then let out,</l>
                  <l>he fiercely rag'd and reigned,</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog's</hi> armed Strength,<note place="margin">Chap. 20.9.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>whom God conſum'd in ire,)</l>
                  <l>The Devil (I ſay) was caſt at length,</l>
                  <l>in Lake of Brimſtone fire.</l>
                  <l>And with him all the damned Race:</l>
                  <l>for God comes on his Throne,</l>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:154167:36"/>
                  <l>A dreadful Judge, before whoſe Face,</l>
                  <l>both Heaven and Earth are gone,</l>
                  <l>And Hell, and Grave, and Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and Land,</l>
                  <l>deliver up their dead;</l>
                  <l>Who all before the Judge do ſtand,</l>
                  <l>and Books are opened;</l>
                  <l>As they have done, Doom doth begin,</l>
                  <l>his Work each one commendeth;</l>
                  <l>The wicked out, the godly in,</l>
                  <l>and ſo the Seſſion endeth.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. <hi>XI.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>NOw doth Saint <hi>John</hi> lively deſcribe,</l>
                  <l>the <hi>Church</hi> her glorious State,</l>
                  <l>Wife of the Lamb, th' eſpouſed Bride,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> heavenly Mate:</l>
                  <l>Who was found worthy to be clad,<note place="margin">Chap. 19.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>in pure and bright Aray:</l>
                  <l>And was exhorted to be glad,</l>
                  <l>againſt her Marriage day.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> New, Holy, Great,</l>
                  <l>from Heaven down deſcending,<note place="margin">Chap. 21.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>God and the Lamb there hold their Seat,</l>
                  <l>it lightning and defending.</l>
                  <l>The Form it is each way four ſquare,</l>
                  <l>the Matter Gold and Pearl,</l>
                  <l>The Citizens more noble are,</l>
                  <l>than earthly Lord or Earl,</l>
                  <l>Twelve Gates there are for Entrance wide,</l>
                  <l>the Porters Angels ſtout,</l>
                  <l>A Wall moſt high on every ſide,</l>
                  <l>doth compaſs it about.</l>
                  <l>The weight of Glory there reſerv'd,</l>
                  <l>can no Man's tongue impart,</l>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:154167:36"/>
                  <l>Eye hath not ſeen, Ear hath not heard,</l>
                  <l>nor enter can Man's Heart.</l>
                  <l>There is no Sorrow, Pain nor Care,<note place="margin">Chap. 22.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>no want of Cloth or Food,</l>
                  <l>No Filth, no Darkneſs, Curſe, nor Fear,</l>
                  <l>No want of any Good.</l>
                  <l>There is of Life the Tree and Spring,</l>
                  <l>the Store-houſe of all Treaſures:</l>
                  <l>There Saints triumph, there Angels ſing,</l>
                  <l>in Paradiſe of Pleaſures.</l>
                  <l>There lives our Head, let us not ſlack,</l>
                  <l>but ever watch and pray:</l>
                  <l>Our Saviour will come quickly back;</l>
                  <l>even ſo, come Lord away.</l>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sine fine ſit Laus Deo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="notes">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:154167:37"/>
               <head>Certain Brief Notes collected out of the late and approved <hi>Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> for the better Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Book of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SAINT <hi>John</hi> received and wrote this <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> or <hi>Revelation</hi> of the Myſteries of God, when he was in <hi>Patmos. Patmos</hi> is an Iſland, lying in the <hi>Aegaean</hi> or <hi>Graecian</hi> Sea, which divideth <hi>Aſia</hi> from <hi>Europe,</hi> whither he was baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Domitian</hi> the perſecuting <hi>Emperour</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> about the Year 96.</p>
               <p>The ſeven Churches to which he wrote were ſeven famous Cities of <hi>Aſia</hi> the leſſer, and <hi>Greece,</hi> where the Goſpel was firſt planted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Seven Seals.</head>
               <p>THE firſt is referred to the times of the Primitive Church, wherein Chriſt by his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Miniſters,</hi> ſubdued Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the obedience of the Goſpel, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:154167:37"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond, is referred to the time of the cruel Perſecutions, under the bloody Emperors, <hi>Caligula, Nero, Domitian;</hi> and the reſt, unto the time of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> who comforted the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third, ſhewing the Plagues of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, Peſtilence and Wars, that followed the Contempt of the Goſpel, is referred, chiefly to the Times of the <hi>Goths, Hunns,</hi> and <hi>Vandals.</hi> (And theſe Plagues come on <hi>Horſeback</hi>) noting the generality or diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of them into many Countries.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth, ſome make to ſignifie a part of the Plagues fore-mentioned: but more probably it ſignifieth <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> as King <hi>James</hi> was of opinion. See more in the Deſcription of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> following; and more at large in that Chriſtian, Learned, and Magnanimous Premonition of his <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Majeſty,</hi> prefixed to his <hi>Apology</hi> for the <hi>Oath of Allegiance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The fifth, ſheweth the ſafe Eſtate of them that have ſuffered for the Truth, being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Altar of God's Protection.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The ſixth, ſheweth great Alterations, and Commotions of States and Kingdoms; the Devil ſtopping the Courſe of the Goſpel; and Chriſt preſerving his, in all Corners of the Earth. <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.2.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> The ſeventh, ſheweth the Effect of the Devil's Rage, namely the ſpringing up of Hereſies, the fall of Miniſters and Teachers, the height of Corruption and Abomination in the Pope and Turk.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:154167:38"/>
               <head>The Seven Trumpets.</head>
               <p>BY theſe, God proclaimeth open War with the World; but his Elect are ſtill in ſafe Eſtate. <hi>Cap.</hi> 8.3.</p>
               <p>The four firſt Trumpets ſhew the hatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Hereſies and Errors, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of them after the firſt 300 Years.</p>
               <p>The three laſt ſhew the full Growth and deviliſh Power of them, in the Pope, and Turk, to the Affliction of the Church and the final Judgment and Torment of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts and Papiſts, denounced by three Woes. <hi>Cap</hi> 8.13.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Deſcription of the Church.</head>
               <p>SHE is called a Woman, <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe without Chriſt her Husband, ſhe is weak and can do nothing.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By Conjunction with Chriſt ſhe bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth Children unto God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe her Love and Affection is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſet on Chriſt her Husband.</p>
               <p>She is clothed with the Sun of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>She treadeth on the Moon, that is, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temneth the World and earthly things.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:154167:38"/>
               <p>She hath a Crown of Twelve Stars, that is, the Doctrin of the Goſpel garniſhed with the Miniſtry of the Twelve Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>She laboureth of Child; namely and firſt of all Jeſus Chriſt the Heir of all; and then of his Members in all Ages. The deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of whom, the Dragon did and doth ſtill watch. <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.4.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Deſcription of the Devil.</head>
               <p>HE is called a Dragon, <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.3. for his Cruelty and Malice: and a red Dragon, for his thirſt and greedy deſire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Blood.</p>
               <p>His ſeven Heads ſhew his manifold ſlights and ſubtilties.</p>
               <p>His ten Horns ſhew his great and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Power.</p>
               <p>His ſeven Crowns, ſignifie the Victories he hath gotten.</p>
               <p>His Tail, of Ambition, Luſt and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, reacheth to Heaven and bruſheth down the third part of the Stars: that is, many of the Miniſters, from their glorious Firmament, to the Earth of Shame and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity. <hi>Verſe</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>This Dragon was chained a thouſand Years. <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.2.</p>
               <p>Theſe years the Learned do account from the 36 Year of the Birth of Chriſt, (for then the Devil began to be mad, becauſe the <hi>Jews</hi> being caſt off, the Church of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles began to increaſe by the power of the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:154167:39"/>Goſpel preached) until the time of Pope <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> or <hi>Gregory</hi> the Seventh, who was a wretched Conjurer, and familiar of the Devil, and therefore a fit Inſtrument at hand, for the Dragon's devilliſh and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Purpoſes, which Rage and Eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs he executed, during the time of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Viols, the laſt ſeven Plagues.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Deſcription of the firſt Beaſt.</head>
               <p>HE is called a Beaſt, <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.1. and ſignifieth in Scripture a Monarchy ſometimes, <hi>Dan</hi> 17.4.</p>
               <p>He is ſaid to riſe out of the Sea; that is, out of the boyling and broyling of heathen Nations, did the great City the Queen of the Nations, or Roman Monarchy ariſe, to tyrannize over the Church of God. <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.15.</p>
               <p>His ſeven Heads ſignifie the ſeven Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments of <hi>Rome,</hi> namely, <hi>Kings, Conſuls, Decemviri, Dictators, Tribuni militum, Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors</hi> and <hi>Biſhops.</hi> Which laſt was not then come when St. <hi>John</hi> wrote. <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.10.</p>
               <p>His ten Heads ſignifie ten Kings, that is, great Power, large Dominion and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
               <p>His ten Crowns ſignifie many Victories: but in that they are on his Horns, and not on his Heads, it ſheweth he prevailed more by his Power, than by Subtilty; contrarily the Dragon, whoſe Heads are ſaid to be crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Or as petty Kings uſe to wear their
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:154167:39"/>Crowns on their Hats, in token of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage they owe, ſo this Beaſt, on his Horns in token of Subjection to the Dragon, of whom he received his Throne and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.2.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Deſcription of Antichriſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the Learned to be four times fully and definitely ſet down in this Book.</head>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP.</hi> 6.8.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt by a pale Horſe,<note place="margin">The firſt Deſcription.</note> having Death for his Rider, Hell for his Convoy, and Power over the fourth part of the Earth (or <hi>Europe</hi>) to kill with the Sword, and with Hunger (or the Famine of the Word, as the black Horſe did by corporal Famine) and by Beaſts, (as Locuſts and Frogs. <hi>Cap.</hi> 9.16.) by whom ſhe procured the Death ſpiritual of Kings and Nations, that drank of the Cup of her Abominations. This being done, the Souls of the Saints cry for Vengeance, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. and their Cry is heard, and Requeſt granted under the ſixth Seal, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP.</hi> 9.1.</head>
                  <p>MOre at large and in this kind,<note place="margin">The ſecond Deſcription.</note> by his Craft and Strength, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He is called a Star fallen from Heaven; or
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:154167:40"/>ſome notable Perſon of great Dignity in the Church: falling like <hi>Lucifer,</hi> from giving light unto the World, and erecting a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom by a noyſom pack of crafty cruel Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min. He hath the key of the bottomleſs Pit: (Or of Hell it ſelf,) whither he ſendeth and letteth in, thouſands of Souls, thorow the ſmoaky Miſts of Darkneſs, Ignorance and Superſtition; out of which Smoak, came thoſe Locuſts (or Abbots, Cardinals, Monks, Friers, Prieſts and Shavelings) which ſting like to Scorpions (or, with damnable Errors and Hereſies) all ſave the green ones of God, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. And theſe ſo ſtung, finding no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in Pardons, Maſſes, Merits, Dirges, Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and the like, ſhall in torment of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſeek for death and not find it, <hi>ver.</hi> 6.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Locuſts are ſtrong and fierce as Horſes; and their Crowns ſhew them to be Conquerors. They have the faces of Men (or fair pretences of Holineſs) but hair of Women (or hearts full of Luſt) Teeth of Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (to catch enough, and hold faſt enough: witneſs the many fat Morſels they did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, where-ever they were ſeated.) Their King is a bad one, or <hi>Abaddon;</hi> the Devil, and his Vicar the Pope, the ſpoylers and deſtroyers of the Church of God. Their Doctrin is ſet down, <hi>ver.</hi> 20. Worſhip of Devils and Idols (or ſpiritual Fornication) Murder (both ſpiritual and corporal) Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery (by Relicks <hi>Agnus Dei</hi>'s, inchanting Prayers to preſerve from Shot, Thunder and the like.) Fornication (corporal, through inordinate Luſts and Lechery, increaſed by Idleneſs and Belly-chear, in both Sexes
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:154167:40"/>reſtrained from holy Marriage, to a filthy monaſtical life, as by many Proofs hath been made apparent,) Theft, (robbing God of his Titles, and beſtowing them on Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt:) and couſening men of their Goods, by Pardons, Jubilees, juggling Wares and Merchandiſe.</p>
                  <p>The deſcription is ended, <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.6. Where the Angel ſweareth, Time ſhall be no more: and the next Angel or ſeventh, blowing the ſeventh Trumpet, doth ſhew the Myſtery of God to be finiſhed <hi>ver.</hi> 7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP.</hi> 18.11.</head>
                  <p>THirdly,<note place="margin">The third Deſcription.</note> by his growth and manner of government. He is called another Beaſt (becauſe he differs from the former (<hi>ver.</hi> 1.) or civil Roman Emperor, in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Juriſdiction, tyrannizing over men by an Eccleſiaſtical Power, which the Emperors had not. He is ſaid to riſe out of the Earth (or from a baſe and low Eſtate, to mount up through the Emperours favour) by little and little. He hath two horns (like the Lamb,) ſignifying his Kingdom and his Prieſthood, his Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Power, which he uſurpeth from Chriſt, but hath indeed from the Dragon; (like whom he ſpake) in all his Decrees, Canons, Practices and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings. He did all that the firſt Beaſt could do, that is, he is ſtrong and mighty, and nothing inferior to the Ethnick Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, priding himſelf in lies and wonders: <hi>ver.</hi> 13. ſending fire of Excommunication <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rom Heaven; deceiving by damnable Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrins
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:154167:41"/>of Devils, <hi>verſe</hi> 14. Killing and burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for Hereticks, all that will not worſhip the Beaſt, and marking all that do worſhip, for ſlaves and vaſſals. And this Mark muſt be ſet in their Foreheads (to ſignifie their Profeſſion, and to acknowledge their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection; or in their right hand) to teſtifie their abſolute actual obedience to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, upon ſuppoſition that he cannot err. None may buy or ſell without this Mark, and therefore Perjury and breach of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and Faith with Chriſtians, is a vertue in a Catholick. Now that <hi>Rome</hi> is this Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Beaſt, the <hi>Number</hi> doth ſignifie and ſhew, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. and <hi>&amp;</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Latine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, Romiſh Faith, Romiſh Church, and ſweareth to it in number and meaſure. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Beaſt are ſeven Viols of God's Wrath and Vengeance, propheſied to be poured out, <hi>Chap</hi> 16. and the ſeventh being emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied, it is ſaid, <hi>that Babylon came in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance before God,</hi> Verſe 19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP.</hi> 17.3.</head>
                  <p>LAſtly, by his dangerous and deadly Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements, as the true Spouſe, (<hi>Chap.</hi> 12.) for here the adulterous Spouſe is liken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a Woman; but yet a Whore, for her ſpiritual Adultery; and drunken with the Blood of the Saints, tho' a gorgeous and glorious Whore in outward ſhew, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. The Inſcription by which ſhe is to be known, is called a Myſtery, <hi>Verſe</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, and ſhe takes her ſelf to be the Viſible Head of the Church, the myſtical
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:154167:41"/>Body of Chriſt, and the Diſpenſer of the Myſteries of God.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, as ſhe deſerves indeed, and as the reſt of her Titles bear witneſs: <hi>verſe</hi> 5. Mother of Whoredoms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or a Myſtery of all Abominations under a pretext of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</p>
                  <p>Now, this Whore of <hi>Babylon, that</hi> rideth on the Beaſt, is not any one Man, but a Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion in Government, <hi>Chap.</hi> 17, 18. The Beaſt is ſaid to have ſeven Heads, <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.1. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.7. Which are expounded to be <hi>Roma Septicollis,</hi> or <hi>Rome</hi> built on ſeven Hills: the names whereof are theſe, <hi>Palatinus, Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinalis, Aventinus, Viminalis, Coelius, Exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus, Capitolinus.</hi> Or elſe ſeven Forms of Government, as is ſhewed before, of which the ſixth, <hi>viz.</hi> (the Government by Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors) was in being, when St. <hi>John</hi> wrote: <hi>Chap.</hi> 17. <hi>ver</hi> 10. The ſeventh was not then come, namely, the Eccleſiaſtical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by Biſhops; which ſucceeded at <hi>Rome,</hi> upon the Tranſlation of the Imperial Seat to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> (and was to continue but a ſhort ſpace) or, about two hundred ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſix Years, <hi>viz.</hi> from the time of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> to the time of <hi>Phocas</hi> the Emperor, who gave to <hi>Boniface Biſhop of Rome,</hi> the Title of Univerſal Biſhop, and Head of all Churches. And by this means (the perfection of defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and Popiſh Corruption coming in) was brought forth the eighth Beaſt, one of the ſeven in ſhew, becauſe ſtill ſeeming to ſucceed the Biſhops in Eccleſiaſtical Form of Government.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="notes">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:154167:42"/>
               <head>The means by which Antichrist ſhall be Confounded.</head>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP.</hi> 11.3.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> THey are called two Witneſſes, and they may ſignifie either the old, and new Teſtaments, both which <hi>Antichrist</hi> hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to diſgrace, deface, corrupt, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs and deſtroy, calling the Scripture a noſe of Wax, and a dead Letter, a leaden Rule; and preferring the Traditions of Men above them. Theſe Witneſſes in the Primitive Church, were cloathed in ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, and preached Repentance, by the ſpace of five or ſix hundred Years. But ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving done their Meſſage, the Roman Beaſt made War upon them, and overcame them, ſo that they lay open to contempt, cared for of none, underſtood of few, and feared of all to be medled withal. (Yea, they were killed) and the very Throat of them cut, by a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Cenſure, Printed at <hi>Venice, An.</hi> 1562. Which condemneth all for heretical, that contradict their Traditions.</p>
                  <p>Thus lay their Bodies without Vigor, <hi>Ver.</hi> 8. (as ſometimes the Law, until it was revived, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.14.) and worldly men rejoyced, <hi>Ver.</hi> 10. for now they had liberty
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:154167:42"/>to do what they liſted, a Pardon for all might be procured by their Purſe.</p>
                  <p>Yet at laſt (praiſed be God) we ſee theſe Witneſſes to ariſe again, and beginning to ſhine in their former Glory, <hi>ver.</hi> 11.</p>
                  <p>Which happy Alteration and Exaltation of them, hath bred ſuch an Earthquake, among the Nations that a good part of them that were in Subjection to that City, are fallen from her, and have rejected her yoke, <hi>Verſe</hi> 13.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or theſe Witneſſes may ſignifie the Preachers of the Word. Two only are mentioned, becauſe two are ſufficient in Law. Theſe for preaching the foreſaid Truth and Doctrin, diſcovering the Man of ſin, and his Corruptions, were put to cruel Deaths and Torments; but roſe again in the perſon of their Succeſſors, ſupplying their room, and ſtill bearing witneſs to the ſame Truth. Of which grew that memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and miraculous Obſervation, <hi>Sanguis Martyrum ſemen Eccleſiae,</hi> the Martyrs Blood the Seed of the Church. The mighty and marvellous power of this Truth, hath of latter times ſo encreaſed, that many King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and great Nations, have in few years been converted thereby, to the true Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Almighty God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="notes">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:154167:43"/>
               <head>The ſeven last laſt Plagues and Viols of <hi>God's</hi> Wrath.</head>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP.</hi> 16.1.</head>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> THe firſt Viol being poured out, there fell a noyſom and grievous Sore. Some underſtand by it the <hi>Pox,</hi> called <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Neapolitanus,</hi> a ſtrange and loathſom Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, which firſt lighted on the ancient chief Crutches and ſupporters of the <hi>Pope;</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Italians, Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Frenchmen,</hi> for their filthy Whoredoms and Beaſtlineſs, in the Year of our Lord, 1494.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond turned the Sea (of the World) into Blood, by <hi>Turkiſh</hi> and <hi>Popiſh</hi> Maſſacres, Murders and mortal Wars.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third ſheweth the Increaſe of that Plague: It cometh home even to the very Doors, their Rivers and Fountains ran Blood.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth, cauſed the Sun (by ſcorch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and drying) to torment with Dearth, Plagues and ſundry Diſeaſes.</p>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:154167:43"/>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The fifth darkened the Kingdom of the Beaſt: which is fulfilled in the Revolt of Proteſtant Princes, from Obedience to the Pope, and it is to them the greateſt Plague of all others, <hi>Verſe</hi> 10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The ſixth dryed up the River <hi>Euphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> (which was the beſt truſted defence of the old <hi>Babylon</hi>) that is, conſumed the Riches, Honour, Glory and Strength of <hi>Romiſh Babylon.</hi> And this maketh the Fiſh, nay, the Frogs, to beſtir themſelves: for it is ſaid, (that three Frogs came out) a plural number; noting their multitude and threefold direction. For, Firſt they are raiſed and inſpired by the Dragon the Devil.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, they are maintained by the Beaſt, <hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And thirdly, they are inſtructed by the falſe Prophet, the <hi>Apoſtatick</hi> Church, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Triple-crowned Monarch the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Frogs they are fitly named, being indeed Animals of either Element, Air, Earth, and Water, croaking in every Corner to ſtop the Leak, to fill up their <hi>Euphrates,</hi> and to gather again the Kings of the Earth, <hi>Verſe</hi> 14.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> The ſeventh Viol foreſhews the final Overthrow of <hi>Rome,</hi> by Rents, Convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:154167:44"/>and Confuſions, Commotions of their City and Kingdom. And in ſo fearful a manner, as may aſtoniſh even thoſe that hear thereof.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Revel. <hi>18.4.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Come out of her my People, that ye be not partakers of her ſins, and that ye receive not of her Plagues.</p>
                  </q>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:154167:44"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:154167:45"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:154167:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
